http://techcrunch.com/2014/12/15/hiptic-games-launches-its-gamethrive-push-notification-service/
<START:organization> Hiptic Games <END> , a <START:organization> Y Combinator <END> alum that ’s been operating in stealth since the summer 2011 batch , has launched <START:organization> GameThrive <END> , a push notification service that aims to help developers engage players when they’re least likely to be annoyed .
Originally built for the team’s own needs , the service combines push-notification delivery automation with analytics tools to avoid overwhelming users to the point where they delete an app .
Looking at things like playing habits and response rates to different notifications , the service schedules messages for in-game deals or events at times when players will be mostly likely to engage with them and come back to the game .
<START:organization> GameThrive <END> is available as a native SDK for <START:organization> iOS <END> , <START:organization> Android <END> , and <START:organization> Windows Phone <END> , but most developers will probably find it easier to build into games using SDKs for popular engines .
With the exception of Unreal , there are kits available for most major mobile engines including <START:organization> Unity <END> and <START:organization> Cocos2d-x <END> .
<START:organization> Corona <END> and <START:organization> Marmalade <END> have actually partnered with <START:organization> Hiptic <END> to make it available directly to developers who download their engines without requiring a separate add-on .
<START:organization> Hiptic <END> CEO <START:person> George Deglin <END> says that most of the 900 developers using the service have been grandfathered in on special beta pricing plans and don’t have to pay until they’re delivering notifications to 8 million devices .
Those signing up now won’t pay if they’re reaching fewer than 1 million devices , with plans starting at $ 49 per month for user bases bigger than that .
As mentioned in the blog post announcing the service’s launch , <START:organization> Hiptic <END> hopes to bring over developers who rely on <START:organization> Urban Airship’s <END> free notification tier , which ends at the end of this month .
They’ve built a tool that automates migrating over from that service using just your credentials .
