http://techcrunch.com/2014/12/15/homejoy-le-pause/
<START:organization> Homejoy <END> , the <START:location> U.S. <END> domestic cleaning startup that ’s backed by the likes of <START:organization> Google Ventures <END> to the tune of $ 38 million , is putting another of its international operations on hold .
Following news earlier today that its Canada-based business is being “paused” , <START:organization> TechCrunch <END> has learned that <START:organization> Homejoy’s <END> activities in <START:location> France <END> have been met with the same fate .
A spokesperson told me that what this means in practice is that the company is no longer accepting bookings in France , while — in a line similar to the one given regarding <START:location> Canada <END> — it ’s maintaining relationships with the cleaners locally who were signed up to its platform , for when ( or if ? ) <START:organization> Homejoy <END> re-enters <START:location> France <END> .
Relationships , of course , can’t be put on hold forever , and it would seem inevitable that those cleaners will now be looking for work elsewhere .
Meanwhile , the company is keen to stress that it remains active in <START:location> Europe <END> — specifically , that it is choosing to focus on <START:location> Germany <END> , where <START:location> Berlin <END> will now act as its European customer service “hub” , and the <START:location> UK <END> where it currently has operations in <START:location> London <END> .
It’s also recently added <START:location> Munich <END> to its German presence , which also includes <START:location> Hamburg <END> .
What’s interesting about <START:organization> Homejoy’s <END> “pausing ” of operations in <START:location> Canada <END> and <START:location> France <END> is that it recently saw a new and potentially formidable competitor in the form of <START:organization> Rocket Internet’s <END> <START:organization> Helpling <END> , which has recently launched its domestic cleaning service in both countries .
<START:location> Paris <END> in particular looks to be heating up as a battleground .
Alongside <START:organization> Helpling <END> , there’s UK-headquartered and Accel-backed <START:organization> Hassle <END> , which actually expanded to the French capital city before the <START:organization> Rocket Internet <END> startup made its way across the border .
Both companies will probably be glad to see the back of <START:organization> Homejoy <END> , at least for now .
You know what they say , if you can’t stand the heat …
