http://techcrunch.com/2014/12/15/mark-zuckerbergs-facebook-profile-under-attack-from-brazilian-trolls/
<START:person> Mark Zuckerberg’s <END> <START:organization> Facebook <END> profile has come under attack from a large number of online trolls who are taking advantage of the opportunity to leave comments , including stickers , photos and other “meme” images , on the <START:organization> Facebook <END> CEO’s public posts .
The attackers are largely based in <START:location> Brazil <END> , and their barrage of comments and jokes have continued for several days now , nonstop .
We’ve heard some reports , via tipsters , that the attack started as some kind of protest against the low reach of <START:organization> Facebook Pages <END> , but that remains unclear .
The messages and comments currently visible don’t speak to any specific agenda or complaint against <START:organization> Facebook <END> or its founder , but rather seem to be random , and sometimes bizarre , posts typical to spam attacks instigated by trolls .
The trolling is taking place on older posts which are further back on Mark <START:person> Zuckerberg’s <END> Timeline .
It appears the attacks began in the comments section of a post in May 2012 where <START:person> Zuckerberg <END> added a “life event ” announcing his marriage to <START:person> Priscilla Chan <END> .
There are now nearly 2 million Likes on that image and 186,400+ comments , most of which are now nonsensical photos and memes , stickers and other random comments .
Few commenters are leaving any text comments of their own .
Another post – this one where <START:person> Zuckerberg <END> announced he became a vegetarian in January 2011 – is also seeing massive abuse , with now over 108,000 comments .
Some of the commenters have even begun leaving images that say things like ( roughly translated ) , “this trolling is out of control . ”
Many also just say “come join the ‘zueira , '” which basically means trolling or disorder .
“Trolling today , trolling tomorrow , trolling forever ” reads one .
“Go go go zoeira” proclaims another .
While it ’s unknown at this time who started the trolling or why , one link in a news article pointed to this <START:organization> Facebook <END> group titled “Flood that <START:person> Mark <END> ” ( translation via <START:organization> Google Translate <END> ) .
The group currently has 1,153 members and instructs them , in Portuguese , to participate in challenges and reminds them “what happens in the group , stays in the group . ”
The group ’s banner image include photos of <START:person> Zuckerberg <END> , his wife and an image that is regularly seen in the trolls ’ <START:organization> Facebook <END> comments .
One commenter on a Brazilian news site said the group would not stop until it reached a record number of comments .
We’ve asked <START:organization> Facebook <END> if it was aware of the abuse , and what , if any , actions it ’s planning to take to stem the flood of comments .
We’ll update if <START:organization> Facebook <END> responds .
