http://techcrunch.com/2014/12/15/these-australian-social-media-reactions-to-the-sydneysiege-are-perfect/
The hostage situation in <START:location> Sydney’s <END> busy city district has crossed over into day two , with the identity of the hostage taker revealed as <START:person> Man Haron Monis <END> .
The perpetrator , 49 , is a self-proclaimed sheikh already pending trial and out on bail for being an accessory to murder .
He still has an unconfirmed number of hostages captured inside a <START:organization> Lindt Cafe <END> in <START:location> Sydney <END> .
Some hostages escaped or were otherwise freed , and police have now stormed the cafe , according to the <START:organization> NYT <END> .
<START:organization> TechCrunch <END> is n’t the place for breaking news on the situation , which can be found here and here .
But as the world watches <START:location> Sydney <END> , we noticed a specific , and now-viral , status update from <START:person> Jason Maggs <END> .
It has now been shared more than 16,000 times on <START:organization> Facebook <END> , noted by <START:organization> FBNewswire <END> , and we’re simply hoping to pass the powerful message along .
He wrote :
<START:person> Jason’s <END> status update is just a small part of Australia’s social media reaction .
The hashtag # IWillRideWithYou is growing in <START:location> Australia <END> , with more than 100k shares across <START:organization> Facebook <END> and <START:organization> Twitter <END> .
The hashtag is meant to express solidarity among Australians as they use public transport , encouraging those religiously dressed to feel safe and those who are not , to feel safe around them .
It was reportedly started by a girl named <START:person> Rachael <END> , who recounted an experience on a public train the morning that the hostage crisis began .
Our thoughts and prayers go out to the hostages , their families , and anyone victimized or involved in the situation .
And also , we agree with <START:person> Jason <END> .
