http://techcrunch.com/2014/12/15/why-its-right-to-report-on-the-sony-hack/
“No one’s private life can totally withstand public scrutiny , ” reads an <START:organization> NYT <END> op-ed penned by screenwriter and playwright <START:person> Aaron Sorkin <END> , angrily blasting the media for reporting the private details revealed through the recent hack of <START:organization> Sony Pictures Entertainment <END> , in what’s shaping up to be one of the largest corporate data breaches to date .
“…Every news outlet that did the bidding of the [hacking group ] <START:organization> Guardians of Peace <END> is morally treasonous and spectacularly dishonorable , ” he adds .
Meanwhile , <START:organization> Sony Pictures <END> – blithely ignoring the First Amendment ( and the <START:person> Streisand <END> effect ) – has threatened legal action against journalists reporting on the findings from the stolen documents .
<START:person> Sorkin <END> and <START:organization> Sony <END> are both wrong .
<START:organization> Sony <END> may be a victim , but there is data in the breach that ’s worth reporting to the public – even if one of the largest takeaways is for other corporations to react to <START:organization> Sony <END> ’s cautionary tale and beef up its own servers and security infrastructure .
<START:organization> Sony <END> Tries Silencing Reporters
One thing the world needs to understand immediately is that all information is public by default , and the only real privacy protection is that its exposure has yet to be targeted by determined hackers .
Over the past several years , hackers have stolen consumers ’ personal information and credit card numbers from some of the largest retailers .
They’ve pulled nude photos off celebrity’s phones and from “private” messaging app <START:organization> Snapchat <END> .
Large companies like <START:organization> Adobe <END> and <START:organization> eBay <END> have seen emails and other personal account information stolen .
And whistleblowers like <START:person> Snowden <END> have revealed the most private and devastating aspects of government spying agendas .
There is literally nothing that is above being exposed publicly if the right people are focused on a specific agenda .
The <START:organization> Sony <END> hack was carried out by a group referring to itself as the <START:organization> “Guardians of Peace <END> . ”
The group has demanded that <START:organization> Sony <END> pull its upcoming movie <START:organization> “The Interview <END> , ” starring <START:person> Seth Rogen <END> and <START:person> James Franco <END> , which was based on a fictional plot to assassinate North Korean leader <START:person> Kim Jong Un <END> .
The group has leaked a number of <START:organization> Sony <END> movies online including the yet-to-be released remake of <START:organization> “Annie <END> , ” plus “Mr.
Turner , ” <START:organization> “Still Alice <END> , ” and <START:organization> “To Write Love on Her Arms <END> , ” alongside large data dumps from inside <START:organization> Sony <END> ’s corporate network .
The reaction , however , of hacking victims like <START:organization> Sony <END> should not include tantrums like those now demonstrated by <START:person> Sorkin <END> and the studio itself .
They should only offer apologies , if they say anything at all .
Apologies for making the hack just so damned easy , keeping some of the company ’s most private information on its operations , its employees ( and their families ) in unencrypted Excel and Word files and carelessly shared emails .
That’s not to blame the victims themselves , though – individuals make mistakes , but corporate IT policies are meant to protect those mistakes from becoming publicly shared data .
<START:organization> Sony Pictures <END> , one of the <START:location> U.S. <END> ’s largest studios , has now , somewhat ridiculously , asked journalists to destroy the stolen documents , and warned that those who did n’t comply will face further action , the company threatened via letters sent to a number of online and print publishers .
<START:organization> “Sony Pictures Entertainment <END> will have no choice but to hold you responsible for any damage or loss arising from such use or dissemination by you , ” the letter states .
News media has reported on a number of these leaked emails , which have included private jabs , jokes and commentary , including a director referring to <START:location> Hollywood <END> star <START:person> Angelina Jolie <END> as a “spoiled brat , ” <START:organization> Sony <END> ’s botching of the <START:person> Steve Jobs <END> movie , and racist riffs between studio co-chairman <START:person> Amy Pascal <END> and producer <START:person> Scott Rudin <END> about what <START:person> President Obama’s <END> favorite movies might be .
One could argue that those sorts of details , as <START:person> Sorkin <END> claims , were exploited for pageviews more so than public good .
But that ’s not looking at the bigger picture related to the media’s coverage of the hack .
Beyond providing fodder for gossip blogs , the <START:organization> Sony <END> hack has also revealed serious information that ’s arguably more serving of the “public interest . ”
( Hint : that ’s what journalists are supposed to cover – a topic , incidentally , that <START:person> Sorkin’s <END> own show <START:organization> HBO’s <END> <START:organization> “The Newsroom” <END> has grappled with recently , when its reporters for a fictional news network resembling <START:organization> CNN <END> landed a treasure trove of stolen <START:organization> Department of Defense <END> documents . )
Worth Revealing ?
The <START:organization> Sony <END> hack has displayed a lot about the failing of our modern , wired corporate culture .
Like just how casual internal company HR employees treat email communication , for example .
Email is not private ; as a former IT worker , I could have accessed any inbox on my domain ( and often did , though not for reading emails , but for legitimate reasons like backup , archiving , or transfer to a new hire ) .
But more importantly , employees dealing with sensitive information seem not to understand that email is not a place where an HR employee needs to be detailing a child’s medical treatment , where that treatment is taking place , the child’s name , how the child was doing in treatment , and more .
<START:organization> Sony <END> , and likely other organizations that are currently fortunate enough to not have their poor security policies exposed , also does not seem to understand that if you’re choosing to record Social Security numbers , birth dates and salaries in Excel spreadsheets , you should protect them with at least a minimum amount of security , by way of encryption .
Or hell , even a password .
( That’s not to say the files could n’t have still been hacked , but it would have made it that much harder . )
In addition , while the hackers may have accessed the files in question illegally , there are insights the files reveal that are worth sharing more broadly .
It’s worth informing the public that the studio’s upper management is 94 percent male , and 88 percent white ( as Fusion reports ) – making them less diverse than the much-lambasted tech companies whose recent barrage of diversity reports have revealed their tendencies toward monoculture , for instance .
Image credit , above : <START:organization> Fusion .net <END>
Another key item that was revealed by journalists reporting on the <START:organization> Sony <END> leak was that of Hollywood’s war against Google , which was code-named “Project Goliath ” in email threads .
As detailed by <START:organization> The Verge <END> , lawyers from the <START:organization> MPAA <END> and half a dozen major studios refer to “Goliath ” as their biggest enemy in their battle with online piracy , and the <START:organization> Sony <END> emails discuss a variety of tactics to fight “Goliath , ” including site blocking , legal action involving state attorneys general , political lobbying , and more .
<START:organization> Sony <END> ’s Emails Could Be Your Emails
<START:person> Sorkin <END> ( and <START:organization> Sony <END> ) are fine to criticize reporters ’ editorial choices .
But <START:person> Sorkin <END> , in a nutshell , is wrong to say that reporting on the leaks is “spectacularly dishonorable ” as a whole .
And neither is he correct in thinking that the right to report should be shut down .
These leaks have contained thousands of Social Security numbers , personnel files containing employee salaries and severance costs , personal information on employees and execs including birth dates , and even health records for dozens of employees , their spouses and their children .
The press is not generally pointing to the actual files in question , hosting them on their own sites in full , or revealing details like which employees had high medical bills , or which child’s medical claims were being denied .
The media has reported , however , that is the kind of information these documents contain .
And it ’s worth doing so : <START:organization> Sony <END> ’s emails could be your emails .
They could be your company ’s emails .
Those could be your kids .
If an organization of <START:organization> Sony <END> ’s size is susceptible to hacking , anyone is .
In the aftermath , <START:organization> Sony <END> has now hired <START:organization> FireEye Inc. <END> ’s <START:organization> Mandiant <END> forensics unit to clean up this massive cyber attack , as the <START:organization> FBI <END> investigates the incident .
But the immediate damage has been done and the damage may continue for some time .
Only a small number of documents have been revealed so far – the hackers reportedly captured over 100 terabytes of data .
Headlines about <START:location> Hollywood <END> actors or ego-damaging asides may draw pageviews ( and may be in poor taste ) , but what’s not up for debate is whether journalists can report on illegally obtained files – they can , thanks to First Amendment protections .
Is there anything in the files that “can help , inform or protect anyone ? , ” asks <START:person> Sorkin <END> , mid-tirade .
Yes , as our above examples show .
But also , more generally , that this happened , that this level of private data can be revealed , and that it can be revealed with ease can help us all .
Let it serve as a warning to everyone from corporate IT to everyday consumers to protect ourselves…or risk becoming the next <START:organization> Sony <END> .
