http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-12-16/european-index-futures-signal-equities-rebound-from-six-day-drop.html
European stocks dropped for a seventh day , erasing earlier gains , as banks and energy companies fell .
The <START:organization> Stoxx Europe 600 Index <END> dropped 0.8 percent to 320.59 at 12:08 p.m. in <START:location> London <END> after climbing as much as 0.7 percent .
Earlier , it lost as much as 1.2 percent as factory data from <START:location> China <END> and <START:location> France <END> missed economists ’ forecasts .
European stocks erased their 2014 gains yesterday , with the <START:organization> Stoxx 600 <END> closing at its lowest level since Oct. 20 .
After rallying 13 percent from this year’s low to an almost seven-year high on Dec. 5 , the index tumbled 7.9 percent in the past six days , dragged down by energy shares .
“There is n’t a positive trigger to vanish the current fear of a major impact due to the drop in oil prices , ” said <START:person> Guillermo Hernandez Sampere <END> , who helps manage about 130 million euros ( $ 163 million ) at MPPM EK in <START:location> Eppstein , Germany <END> .
“The hope for a year-end rally is very little , too many issues need to be resolved in the near term , to switch back to risk-on mode . ”
<START:organization> Societe Generale SA <END> and <START:organization> ING Groep NV <END> slid more than 3 percent , pushing a gauge of bank shares down 1.4 percent for the worst performance among 19 industry groups on the <START:organization> Stoxx 600 <END> .
<START:organization> Premier Oil Plc <END> and <START:organization> Technip SA <END> declined at least 1.8 percent , helping send a gauge of oil and gas stocks down for a seventh day .
Crude extended losses , trading below $ 55 a barrel for the first time since May 2009 , amid speculation that <START:location> U.S. <END> producers may further increase output as they battle <START:organization> OPEC <END> for market share .
<START:organization> Repsol SA <END> ( REP ) dropped 3.4 percent after saying it will buy <START:organization> Talisman Energy Inc. <END> for $ 8 per common share in a cash deal .
<START:organization> Orange SA <END> rose 1.3 percent after <START:organization> BT Group Plc <END> started exclusive talks to acquire <START:organization> EE <END> , the British wireless venture it owns with <START:organization> Deutsche Telekom AG <END> , for 12.5 billion pounds ( $ 19.6 billion ) .
To contact the reporter on this story : <START:person> Jonathan Morgan <END> in <START:location> Frankfurt <END> at jmorgan157@bloomberg .net
