http://www.sfgate.com/news/world/article/Korean-Air-to-be-sanctioned-for-nut-rage-cover-up-5959120.php
<START:location> SEOUL , South Korea <END> ( AP ) — <START:location> South Korea <END> 's transport ministry said <START:organization> Korean Air Lines Co. <END> will face sanctions for pressuring employees to lie during a government probe into the nut rage fiasco that highlighted the tyrannical behavior of a top Korean business family .
The ministry said Tuesday it will also evaluate if the airline 's corporate culture poses safety risks after its chairman 's daughter <START:person> Cho Hyun -ah <END> overruled the captain of a flight to force the plane back to the gate in the incident early this month .
<START:person> Cho <END> , who was head of cabin service at <START:organization> Korean Air <END> , ordered a senior flight attendant off a Dec. 5 flight after she was served macadamia nuts in a bag , instead of on a plate , in what she thought was a breach of service protocol in first class .
Transport ministry director <START:person> Lee Gwang -hee <END> said <START:organization> Korean Air <END> could face 21 days of flight suspensions or a $ 1.3 million fine for violating aviation law .
The punishment will be determined by a separate committee that could decide to increase or lessen it .
<START:person> Cho <END> family members have a direct 10 percent stake in <START:organization> Korean Air <END> , which is part of the family 's <START:organization> Hanjin <END> conglomerate .
<START:person> Park Chang-jin <END> , the crew member who had to disembark from the plane , told <START:location> South Korea <END> 's <START:organization> KBS <END> television network on Friday that <START:person> Cho <END> had shamed and insulted crew members .
A first-class passenger told <START:organization> Yonhap News Agency <END> that <START:person> Cho <END> yelled at flight attendants who kneeled before her , pushed one flight attendant 's shoulder and threw an object at the cabin wall .
The incident now dubbed "nut rage " hogged headlines around the world and enraged the South Korean public , leading to <START:person> Cho <END> 's removal from all executive roles at the airline .
The 40-year-old and her father apologized last week , but a new furor has erupted over <START:organization> Korean Air <END> 's attempt to foil government investigators and local media reports that exposed how <START:organization> Korean Air <END> employees were treated like servants of the <START:person> Cho <END> family .
" If the incident itself were not beastly enough , <START:organization> Korean Air <END> 's response has been abominable , " <START:organization> Korea Herald <END> said in an editorial .
" In attempts that are akin to feudal servants trying to protect their lord 's daughter , <START:organization> Korean Air <END> staff rallied to the rescue of <START:organization> Korean Air <END> CEO <START:person> Cho Yang-ho <END> 's daughter . "
<START:person> Park <END> , the crew member , was visited by <START:organization> Korean Air Lines <END> officials who pressured him to give a sanitized version of events to investigators .
The airline will be punished because <START:person> Cho <END> and <START:person> Park <END> lied during the probe and because the captain was negligent in his duties , according to the ministry .
However , the captain wo n't face any sanction as he was powerless to refuse a member of the family that controls the airline , said <START:person> Lee <END> , the transport official .
The ministry 's statement indicated other airline employees also faced pressure to lie to the investigators .
It did not identify them .
Its investigation found <START:person> Cho <END> used abusive language to flight attendants but could not ascertain if she used violence .
It will file a complaint against <START:person> Cho <END> with prosecutors later in the day .
Prosecutors earlier launched a separate investigation into the <START:organization> Korean Air <END> case after receiving a complaint from a civic group .
Prosecutors summoned <START:person> Cho <END> to be questioned on Wednesday , according to <START:organization> Yonhap <END> .
The incident also highlighted the risks of investing in family-controlled companies where the primary goal is to further the interests of the family , not that of the shareholders or employees .
Shares of <START:organization> Korean Air <END> closed 0.3 percent lower after dropping nearly 6 percent in <START:location> Seoul <END> after the government announced its plan to sanction the airline .
