http://www.siliconbeat.com/2014/12/15/spain-regrets-google-news-shutdown/
On the eve of <START:organization> Google <END> pulling the plug on <START:organization> Google News <END> in <START:location> Spain <END> , the Spanish newspaper publishers who had pushed for a stringent new copyright law seem to be having second thoughts about irking the <START:location> Silicon Valley <END> tech giant .
<START:organization> Google <END> has said it will shut down <START:organization> Google News <END> in <START:location> Spain <END> on Tuesday and remove all Spanish publishers from its global news index .
The reason for the unprecedented move ( <START:organization> Google News <END> has never pulled out of a country before ) is a new Spanish law taking effect Jan . 1 that would force the <START:location> U.S. <END> company and other news aggregators to pay Spanish publishers to display snippets of their news stories and link to them .
The <START:organization> Spanish Newspaper Publishers ’ Association <END> , or <START:organization> AEDE <END> , pushed for the copyright rules that lawmakers passed this fall .
But now the same newspaper lobby group tells <START:organization> The Spain Report <END> that it wants the Spanish government or <START:location> European Union <END> to stop <START:organization> Google News <END> from shutting down tomorrow “to protect the rights of citizens and businesses . ”
I spoke this weekend with <START:person> Pipo Serrano <END> , a journalist and professor at the <START:organization> University of Barcelona <END> , who said a lot of Spaniards are likely to be upset at their government , but probably not at <START:organization> Google <END> , when <START:organization> Google News <END> begins blocking Spanish news tomorrow .
Readers will still be able to search for Spain-originated news stories on <START:organization> Google’s <END> main search engine , just not <START:organization> Google News <END> , which uses a different algorithm .
When it comes to the Internet , “the Spanish government does n’t know how to manage this , ” <START:person> Serrano <END> said .
“Instead of realizing we are in a new era , a new time , we’re trying to put patches on everything , trying to keep the old way working . ”
<START:organization> Google <END> has described its 13-year-old <START:organization> Google News <END> service as a “go-away ” site that helps news organizations by sending users directly to the original source of the news they are searching for .
It indexes content from 65,000 publishers in 30 languages , though the company will not say how many publishers and users it has in <START:location> Spain <END> .
“They’re not acting as vultures , picking up everything to enrich their business , ” <START:person> Serrano <END> said .
“The truth is that what <START:organization> Google <END> does is just show the title , the abstract , then redirects people to the newspapers . ”
His perspective echoes what <START:person> Richard Gingras <END> , head of <START:organization> Google News <END> , said in a statement last week announcing the shutdown .
“This new legislation requires every Spanish publication to charge services like <START:organization> Google News <END> for showing even the smallest snippet from their publications , whether they want to or not , ” <START:person> Gingras <END> said .
“As <START:organization> Google News <END> itself makes no money ( we do not show any advertising on the site ) this new approach is simply not sustainable . ”
Though nicknamed the <START:organization> “Google <END> Tax ” because the new Spanish law targeted the giant <START:location> U.S. <END> search engine , the copyright changes also met opposition from homegrown tech entrepreneurs such as <START:person> Ricardo Galli <END> , founder of Spanish social news website <START:organization> Menéame <END> .
<START:person> Galli <END> in recent days used Twitter to mock the publishing lobby and his country ’s conservative <START:organization> Popular Party <END> for passing the law , and has previously threatened to move his business to another country .
Publishers in other Europeans countries have also fought for <START:organization> Google <END> to pay them for linked content but none went as far as <START:location> Spain <END> .
Unlike in <START:location> Germany <END> , where most news organizations opted to stay on the <START:organization> Google News <END> index even if the company did not pay them , the Spanish law would have barred <START:organization> Google <END> from displaying news snippets and headlines even if the publications wanted the exposure without compensation .
Above : A man reads the front page of Spanish newspaper <START:organization> “El Pais <END> ” on Thursday at a bar in <START:location> Pamplona <END> , in northern <START:location> Spain <END> .
<START:organization> Google <END> announced Thursday it will close <START:organization> Google News <END> in <START:location> Spain <END> and block reports from Spanish publishers from more than 70 <START:organization> Google News <END> international editions due to a new Spanish law requiring aggregators to pay to link content .
