http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/business/asian-stocks-mostly-lower/1532490.html
<START:location> HONG KONG <END> : Asian markets mostly slipped on Tuesday ( Dec 16 ) following a sell-off in <START:location> Europe <END> and the <START:location> United States <END> , as oil prices plunged to more than five-year lows and data indicated Chinese manufacturing activity shrank in December .
The dollar and euro edged lower against the yen after losing pace on Monday due to the uncertainty created by weak crude prices , which have increased pressure on <START:location> Russia <END> 's economy and spooked investors .
<START:location> Tokyo <END> tumbled 2.01 per cent , or 344.08 points , to finish at 16,755.32 .
<START:location> Sydney <END> fell 0.65 per cent , or 33.78 points , to 5,152.3 and <START:location> Seoul <END> lost 0.85 per cent , or 16.23 points , to end at 1,904.13 .
<START:location> Hong Kong <END> stocks ended 1.55 per cent lower , giving up 357.35 points to 22,670.5 , but <START:location> Shanghai <END> jumped 2.31 per cent , or 68.10 points , to 3,021.52 .
In <START:location> China <END> , banking giant <START:organization> HSBC <END> said its preliminary index of manufacturing activity came in at 49.5 this month , compared with 50 in November .
Anything below 50 points to contraction and anything above shows growth .
The figures are the latest in a long line that show the world 's number two economy is slowing .
However , <START:location> Shanghai <END> shares advanced - extending a recent bull run - on hopes the government will introduce new measures to spur growth .
<START:organization> Nomura <END> economists said : " The greater-than-expected decline ... raises the possibility that December data will disappoint .
We expect more policy easing to help stabilise growth and to achieve the annual growth target of around 7.5 per cent for 2014 ."
Oil-linked firms are being hammered after crude prices plunged by about half from their June highs , weighed down by an oversupply on world markets , falling demand and <START:organization> OPEC <END> 's decision to maintain high output levels .
Despite the benefits cheap oil brings to some , global stock markets have been dragged down by energy giants and analysts warn there could be further falls on the way .
On Tuesday US benchmark <START:location> West Texas <END> Intermediate for January delivery fell 33 cents to US$ 55.58 while Brent crude for January shed US$ 1.43 to US$ 59.63 in early <START:location> London <END> trade , tumbling below the US$ 60 mark for the first time since mid-2009 .
'MORE PAIN IN STORE'
US shares tumbled on Monday , with the Dow off 0.58 per cent , the S&P 500 falling 0.63 per cent and the <START:organization> Nasdaq <END> slumping 1.04 per cent .
Earlier on Monday <START:location> London <END> 's FTSE 100 ended down 1.87 per cent , while equity markets in <START:location> France <END> and <START:location> Germany <END> fell more than 2.5 per cent .
" Oil prices continue to slide , and that is now the chief worry to <START:location> Russia <END> , which is essentially an oil-exporting economy , " <START:person> Yoshihiro Okumura <END> , general manager at <START:organization> Chibagin Asset Management <END> , told <START:organization> Dow Jones Newswires <END> .
" The creeping fear is that <START:location> Russia <END> may default , reminding investors of the prior Greek fiscal panic , and require a bailout .
Beyond that , a 'domino effect ' of worsening fiscal conditions at other oil-exporting nations may take hold .
Oil prices look far from settled at the mid-$ 50 level , so more pain may yet be in store . "
<START:location> Moscow <END> was forced to ramp up interest rates early on Tuesday , to 17 per cent from 10.5 per cent , after the rouble plunged to a record low against the dollar .
The slide came as the Russian central bank said weak oil prices could lead to a contraction of nearly five per cent next year and as tensions with the United States over the <START:location> Ukraine <END> crisis increased .
In Asian trade the rouble slipped again , sitting at 64.23 to the dollar before rebounding sharply to 59 in initial exchanges in <START:location> Moscow <END> on Tuesday .
However , the uncertainty pushed the yen up against the dollar as traders looked for safer investments .
The dollar was buying 짜117.12 on Tuesday against 짜117.81 in <START:location> New York <END> .
The euro was at 짜146.02 from 짜146.50 , and US$ 1.2468 from US$ 1.2435 .
The yen is considered a safe haven in times of turmoil .
Gold was at US$ 1,199.36 an ounce compared with US$ 1,210.54
late on Monday .
In other markets :
-- <START:location> Mumbai <END> fell 1.97 per cent , or 538.12 points to end at 26,781.44 points .
<START:organization> Sesa Sterlite <END> slid 7.77 per cent to 194.05 rupees , while IT giant <START:organization> Tata Consultancy Services <END> gained 3.40 per cent to 2443.15 rupees .
-- Bangkok closed down 1.13 per cent or 16.75 points to 1,461.74 .
<START:organization> Bangchak Petroleum <END> dropped 4.07 per cent to 29.50 baht , while oil firm <START:organization> PTT Exploration and Production <END> plunged 5.16 per cent to 101.00 baht .
-- <START:location> Malaysia <END> 's main stock index fell 23.37 points or 1.37 per cent to close at 1,673.94 .
<START:organization> Malayan Banking <END> went down 3.60 per cent to 8.29 ringgit , while <START:organization> AMMB Holdings <END> went up 0.16 per cent to 6.20 .
<START:organization> British American Tobacco <END> fell 2.94 per cent to 64.76 .
-- <START:location> Jakarta <END> closed down 1.61 per cent , or 82.40 points , at 5,026.03 .
Palm oil producer <START:organization> Astra Agro Lestari <END> lost 2.70 per cent to 22,500 rupiah , while <START:organization> Hero Supermarket <END> rose 0.21 per cent to 2,420 rupiah .
-- <START:location> Singapore <END> closed down 2.40 per cent , or 79.05 points , to 3,215.09 .
<START:organization> United Overseas Bank <END> fell 3.49 per cent to S$ 23.25 while <START:organization> Singapore Telecom <END> finished down 2.77 per cent at S$ 3.86 .
-- <START:location> Taipei <END> fell 0.39 per cent , or 34.72 points , to 8,950.91 .
<START:organization> Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Co <END> shed 2.21 per cent to NT$ 133.0 while <START:organization> Hon Hai Precision Industry <END> closed 1.94 per cent lower at NT$ 86.0.
-- <START:location> Wellington <END> was flat , edging down 3.32 points to 5,495.75 .
<START:organization> Contact Energy <END> eased 0.48 per cent to NZ$ 6.17 and <START:organization> Fletcher Building <END> was off 0.99 percent at NZ$ 7.97 .
-- <START:location> Manila <END> closed 1.58 per cent lower , shedding 115.24 points to 7,160.38.
<START:organization> SM Prime Holdings <END> dropped 1.76 per cent to 16.70 pesos and <START:organization> Universal Robina Corp. <END> ended 1.22 per cent down at 194.00 pesos , but <START:organization> Philippine Long Distance Telephone <END> rose 0.85 per cent to 2,864.00 pesos .
