http://bdnews24.com/business/2014/12/03/malaysia-also-keen-to-cut-trade-deficit-with-bangladesh
Joint commission meetings will be held as early as next year , it was decided during <START:person> Prime Minister Najib Razak’s <END> meeting with His counterpart <START:person> Sheikh Hasina <END> at his <START:location> Putra Jaya <END> office on Wednesday .
The two sides will discuss ways to close trade gaps and to reach an agreement on free trade , said <START:person> Foreign Secretary Md Shahidul Haque <END> .
“The Malasian prime minister said ‘we already enjoy a very good relationship with <START:location> Bangladesh <END> .
We want to take it to greater heights’ . ”
“There aren’t any irritants between us , he said .
He began speaking by saying he wants to better our relationship , ” Haque added .
<START:location> Malasia <END> exports nearly $ 2 billion worth goods to <START:location> Bangladesh <END> while $ 135 million worth goods goes to the Southeast Asian country from <START:location> Bangladesh <END> .
<START:person> Haque <END> told reporters that both countries had agreed in enhancing trade and commerce as the present rate of business was disproportionately imbalanced and in favour of <START:location> Malasia <END> .
He said the Malasian prime minister recognised the issue and indicated that initiatives would be taken to reduce the gap .
<START:person> Razak <END> greeted <START:person> Hasina <END> when her motorcade reached <START:location> Pardana Putra <END> from <START:location> Hotel Grand Hyatt <END> , where a red carpet and honour guards awaited the <START:location> Bangladesh <END> premier .
The two heads of government held discussions after the initial formalities at the <START:location> Perdana <END> meeting room , where two MoUs , an agreement and a protocol for exporting more workers from <START:location> Bangladesh <END> were signed .
<START:location> Malasia <END> , a large manpower market for <START:location> Bangladesh <END> , currently has about 600,000 Bangladeshis employed at various sectors .
The protocol signed on Wednesday would create jobs for 12,000 more workers from <START:location> Bangladesh <END> initially and in phases 60,000 workers would be recruited .
<START:location> Bangladesh <END> has been proposing a Free Trade Agreement (FTA ) with <START:location> Malasia <END> for a long time .
The foreign secretary said <START:person> Razak <END> agreed to start negotiations on the proposal .
" I think it 's a big step , " said <START:person> Haque <END> .
<START:person> Hasina <END> during the meeting had urged <START:person> Razak <END> to widen the quota-and duty-free access of Bangladeshi goods , chiefly pharmaceuticals , jute goods , cement and footwear , in <START:location> Malasia <END> .
The Malasian premier also assured her on the issue .
The last meeting of the joint commission , formed for better cooperation , was held in <START:location> Dhaka <END> in 2005 .
<START:person> Secretary Haque <END> said <START:location> Malasia <END> had agreed to convene the next meeting there in 2015 .
He said <START:person> Hasina <END> proposed to form a Bangladesh-Malasia investment forum .
" The issue will be discussed in the next joint commission meeting . "
