http://curbed.com/archives/2014/12/15/brutalism-the-game-bbc-tv-show.php
First came <START:organization> AMC <END> 's <START:organization> Mad Men <END> , whose brown <START:organization> Frigidaires <END> and <START:organization> Eero Saarinen <END> tables helped ignite a craze for everything midcentury , modern , and whiskey-spiked .
Now <START:person> Amanda Kolson Hurley <END> writes for <START:organization> City Lab <END> that <START:organization> BBC America <END> 's <START:organization> The Game <END> is poised to do the same for <START:organization> Brutalism <END> .
In the spy thriller , " surprisingly intimate " concrete rooms are practically characters in and of themselves .
The spy HQ , what with its "rough , ribbed-concrete walls , " takes the harshest parts of the style and inhabits it with real human being feelings again .
What 's more , the building is actually home to the good guys rather than sociopaths .
Here a Brutalist icon serves as the hub for a bunch of well-dressed folk fighting for Queen and country .
As <START:person> Hurley <END> writes , "it makes Brutalism the scene of interactions that for once are n't thuggish or sinister . "
[ <START:organization> City Lab <END> ]
