http://curbed.com/archives/2014/12/15/la-shed-architecture-de-gaspe-renovation.php
Photo by <START:person> Maxime Brouillet <END> via <START:organization> Dwell <END>
In the hands of Canadian firm <START:organization> La SHED Architecture <END> , a dreary , well-worn duplex in <START:location> Montreal <END> is now completely unrecognizable .
Gone are the odd wallpaper and aged furnishings : after a massive renovation last year , the 2,700-square-foot home is all about bright lighting , vibrant colors , and versatile spaces .
As <START:organization> Dwell <END> notes , the architects only preserved the building 's "overall shape and footprint . "
Otherwise , the changes are drastic .
A new open-plan area for the kitchen and double-height living room has been opened up , with a home office hovering on the mezzanine above .
The kitchen has been recast in white lacquer and outfitted with stainless-steel countertops .
Standing out in the whole space is the intense orange-lacquer staircase right by the steel bookshelves .
Other transformations include the master bath , where a larger skylight showers the polished space with natural light , as well as the new patio carved out from the middle of the second floor .
Of course , with a budget of $ 400K , which is what was reported on the project page , this sort of extreme makeover is to be expected .
Here are some before-and-afters of the house 's kitchen , master bath , and rear .
Before :
Photo by <START:organization> La Shed Architecture <END> via <START:organization> Facebook <END>
After :
Photo by <START:person> Maxime Brouillet <END> via <START:organization> Dwell <END>
Before :
Photo by <START:organization> La Shed Architecture <END> via <START:organization> Facebook <END>
After :
Photo by <START:person> Maxime Brouillet <END> via <START:organization> Dwell <END>
Before :
Photo by <START:organization> La Shed Architecture <END> via <START:organization> Facebook <END>
After :
Photo by <START:person> Maxime Brouillet <END> via <START:organization> Dwell <END>
路 A Concrete and Glass Home Frames Epic Views of <START:location> San Diego <END> <START:organization> [Dwell <END> ] 路 All <START:organization> La Shed Architecture <END> posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ] 路 All Renovations posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ] 路 All Extreme Makeovers posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ]
