http://curbed.com/archives/2014/12/15/le-palais-royale-florida-photos.php
Photo by <START:person> Brian Nieblas <END>
Back in September , a deeply Ft .
Lauderdale spectacle by the name of <START:location> Le Palais Royal <END> hopped on the market at a staggering $ 139M , instantly becoming <START:location> America <END> 's most expensive home for sale .
Since then , the yet-to-be-completed megamansion has been dethroned by an $ 195M Beverly Hills compound and is now the country 's third most expensive listing , right behind the $ 140M <START:location> Hamptons <END> pad that listed last month .
Now , a fresh batch of construction photos show that , to the horror of <START:organization> Curbed <END> commenters who deemed the property " the Titanic of mansions , " a "pulsating nightmare , " an "architecturally bastardized mess , " the home is coming along exactly as promised by the initial renderings .
Expected to be completed next summer , the 60,000-square-foot palace will offer 11 bedrooms , a 492-foot private dock , an underground garage for over 30 cars , " the first-ever <START:organization> IMAX <END> Theater contracted for private use , " and a $ 2M marble staircase—the enticing makings of a property that , according to listing agent <START:person> William Pierce <END> , has attracted " a great deal of interest " from buyers around the world .
Below , new construction photos , plus an updated set of interior and exterior renderings .
· <START:location> 935 Hillsboro Mile <END> <START:organization> [Coldwell Banker <END> ] · $ 139M <START:location> Florida <END> Spectacle is America 's Most Expensive Listing ( now third most expensive ) <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ] · All Blockbusters posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ]
