http://curbed.com/archives/2014/12/15/nyc-american-museum-of-natural-history-jeanne-gang.php
Photo via <START:organization> Wikipedia <END>
Following in the footsteps of the <START:organization> Museum of Modern Art <END> and the <START:organization> Frick Collection <END> , both of which have big expansions in the works , <START:location> New York City <END> 's renowned <START:organization> American Museum of Natural History <END> has also just announced plans for a major addition to its landmarked campus on the <START:location> Upper West Side <END> .
The new <START:organization> Richard Gilder Center for Science , Education , and Innovation <END> , intended to be completed in time for the museum 's 150th anniversary in 2019 , will be designed by starchitect <START:person> Jeanne Gang <END> , who most recently unveiled a provocative installation on climate change in <START:location> Miami <END> .
Adding 180,000 square feet of new space to existing museum space , the $ 325M project will dedicate altogether 218,000 square feet to science-focused exhibitions , labs , and theaters .
As <START:organization> Curbed NY <END> comments , backlash to the project is certain , considering current controversy over a church-to-condo conversion in the same neighborhood .
Stay tuned .
[ <START:organization> ArchDaily <END> ]
