http://www.breitbart.com/Big-Journalism/2014/12/13/Berkeley-Hecklers-Expose-Free-Speech-Movement-Fraud
Fourteen years ago at the <START:organization> University of California’s <END> flagship campus , a similar mob , including many looking like they had crawled out from under a dock in the marina at the end of University Avenue , drowned my words with shouts of “murderer , ” “racist , ” and “Nazi . ”
They attempted to rip the microphone cord from the wall .
A hirsute man “mooned ” me .
And , in one last indignity , the hecklers seized my writings to fuel an actual book burning .
This all happened under the watchful eyes of two pleasant Cal policewomen , who intervened only when a frustrated man petitioned the hecklers to permit me to speak .
Indeed , during the event the organizers asked me to note the just-discovered presence of the officers in hopes that it might bring order .
“They’ve been here the whole time , ” mocked a heckler .
“We f---ing invited the police . ”
Back then , <START:person> Mumia Abu-Jamal <END> , a cab driver who murdered a <START:location> Philadelphia <END> cop in 1981 , served as the rationale to shout down an invited speaker .
On Wednesday , <START:person> Eric Garner <END> and <START:person> Michael Ferguson <END> , two African Americans killed in encounters with the police under very different circumstances , gave the protestors an excuse to silence an invited guest--and commit violence and the destruction of property in the city surrounding the campus this past week .
The student censors in 2000 and 2014 failed to grasp their own irony .
In my case , a protestor held aloft a sign reading “Fight Racist Censorship ” as he marched around a bonfire containing copies of my 44-page booklet , Cop Killer : How <START:person> Mumia Abu-Jamal <END> Conned Millions into Believing He Was Framed .
In <START:person> Thiel’s <END> case , the billionaire reportedly readied to answer a question on political speech when the mob silenced his speech .
Between the book burning I experienced and the heckler’s veto <START:person> Peter Thiel <END> endured , that parochial inability to step outside of their shoes to understand the hypocrisy they project played out in the shameful prevention of <START:person> Benjamin Netanyahu <END> from speaking on campus in 2000 , the 2001 mass thefts of newspapers containing an ad from <START:person> David Horowitz <END> criticizing the notion of slavery reparations for African Americans , the firebombing of the home of school chancellor <START:person> Robert Birgeneau <END> in 2009 by activists shouting— What else ? —“ No justice , no peace , ” and the effort this fall to revoke an invitation for comedian <START:person> Bill Maher <END> to address the school’s graduates .
The home of the <START:organization> Free Speech Movement <END> of the 1960s now serves as the focal point of campus intolerance .
The unfortunate development has its roots in the self-righteous radicals who championed the <START:organization> Free Speech Movement <END> a half century ago .
In the fall of 1964 , <START:person> Mario Savio <END> applied lessons learned in the civil-rights movement in the <START:location> Deep South <END> to <START:location> Berkeley <END> .
Activists wished to allow off-campus groups to proselytize their views on public walkways .
The school , seeing itself as an institution of higher learning rather than a political convention , balked .
<START:person> Savio <END> implored students to “put your bodies upon the gears and upon the wheels ” of the machine , i .e . , the <START:organization> University of California-Berkeley <END> .
The machine arrested <START:person> Savio <END> that December as he agitated for expanded speech .
Less than two years later , the cops arrested <START:person> Savio <END> for trying to muzzle the speech of military recruiters seeking to meet with interested students on the <START:location> Berkeley <END> campus .
“ Free speech for me—but not for thee , ” as <START:person> Nat Hentoff <END> would say .
The figurehead of the <START:organization> Free Speech Movement <END> misunderstood his campus movement to the point of delusion .
“Last summer I went to <START:location> Mississippi <END> to join the struggle there for civil rights , ” <START:person> Savio <END> explained .
“This fall I am engaged in another phase of the same struggle , this time in <START:location> Berkeley <END> . ”
Affluent students weren’t the equivalent of oppressed blacks , <START:location> Sproul Hall <END> was n’t the <START:location> Edmund Pettus Bridge <END> , and <START:location> Berkeley <END> police officers weren’t Ku Klux Klan Kleagles , or , as <START:person> Savio <END> maintained , American versions of <START:person> Adolf Eichmann <END> .
The sanctimony unleashed by the conflation of every campus controversy into a life-and-death struggle for justice predictably resulted in a complete disregard for the rights of others .
This month , fifty years after <START:person> Mario Savio <END> used a police car as a platform and a bullhorn as a microphone , journalists chronicled the <START:organization> Free Speech Movement <END> on its own terms rather than as a euphemism for radical rule-or-ruinism .
“ I think about the <START:organization> Free Speech Movement <END> as helping to end the <START:person> McCarthy <END> era , ” <START:organization> NYU <END> professor <START:person> Robert Cohen <END> told the AP in a story commemorating the anniversary of the <START:location> Berkeley <END> unrest , which , incidentally , occurred exactly a decade after the <START:location> Wisconsin <END> politician’s formal condemnation by the <START:organization> U.S. Senate <END> .
The delusion of the <START:organization> FSM’s <END> leading man proved contagious .
Even mobs burning books or attempting to burn a physicist-cum-administrator’s home can’t shake the notion that <START:location> Berkeley <END> somehow means what <START:person> John Peter Zengler <END> does .
As <START:person> Peter Thiel <END> discovered this week , you get to speak at Berkeley—if the audience agrees .
