http://www.buffalonews.com/city-region/development/a-forgotten-road-now-turning-heads-and-opening-up-opportunities-20141215
<START:location> Ohio Street <END> , once pitted and cracked , now has fresh asphalt – along with a bike trail and new streetlights being hooked up – after an $ 11 million project to turn it into an <START:location> Outer Harbor <END> gateway .
Now attention turns to transforming the blighted area surrounding the old industrial street into a vibrant neighborhood .
That is what a couple of established developers look to do , with projects to build luxury apartments , an office building and boat docks along the <START:location> Buffalo River <END> .
For years , dump trucks , cement mixers and tractor-trailers made up most of the traffic passing through the once-industrial area , so it could be tough to ride a bicycle on the road .
But the planned rowing club , park and housing developments figure to draw more people .
And a 12-foot-wide bike trail along the road will be attractive to cyclists .
The idea , of course , is that the improvements will resuscitate the area .
<START:person> Carl Paladino <END> said he expects to begin building three or four apartment buildings , each three or four stories high , next year .
The developer said boat docks and window views would make his apartments , on six acres of land , something special .
“We want to get the buildings in the air as much as possible to gain the nice visuals down there , and we are creating boat docks for tenants who want to have their boats parked outside their apartments , ” <START:person> Paladino <END> said .
“This will be a significant improvement for the river and the neighborhood . ”
<START:person> Paladino <END> also plans a two - or three-story office building on five acres of land across the street , with construction beginning when he finds a tenant .
<START:person> Sam Savarino <END> plans 78 luxury apartments in a five-story building at <START:location> Ohio <END> and <START:person> South <END> streets , also with boat docks .
Next month he intends to tear down the former <START:organization> Erie Freight House <END> , near the <START:location> Ohio Street Bridge <END> , ahead of the spring groundbreaking , with the project’s completion targeted for spring 2016 .
“It’s exciting to be down there .
All the other developments will only make it better on Ohio Street , ” <START:person> Savarino <END> said .
<START:person> Rep. Brian Higgins <END> , D-Buffalo , and <START:person> Tom Dee <END> , president of <START:organization> Erie Canal Harbor Development Corp. <END> , cite <START:location> Ohio Street’s <END> improvement as an example of how investment in infrastructure can lead to further waterfront development .
The <START:location> Ohio Street <END> project is intended to create an attractive link between the <START:location> Inner and Outer Harbors <END> .
The project , which is due to be completed by June 2015 , is transforming the 1.4-mile road between <START:location> Michigan Avenue <END> and <START:location> Fuhrmann Boulevard <END> into a two-lane parkway with bike and pedestrian paths , along with attractive landscaping and decorative lighting and signage .
Federal funds are paying for 80 percent of the $ 11 million gateway project , with the <START:organization> City of Buffalo <END> and the <START:organization> Erie Canal Harbor Development Corp. <END> also contributing .
Infrastructure improvements from <START:location> Michigan Avenue <END> to <START:location> Canalside <END> are also planned .
The street’s first sign of revival came in 2011 , with the opening of <START:location> Buffalo RiverFest Park <END> .
Since then , a cluster of grain elevators known as <START:location> Silo City <END> on <START:location> Childs Street <END> , off <START:location> Ohio <END> , has become an arts destination .
In addition , <START:organization> Buffalo RiverWorks <END> can be found on the other side of the river , where hockey and curling on two rinks began taking place last week .
The 6,000-capacity entertainment and events center , which also will include roller derby , will be formally unveiled in February , followed by the opening of a brewery and malting facility later in the year on the <START:location> Ganson Street <END> site .
<START:person> Paladino <END> held onto the land on which he is now planning to build housing for three decades .
Why develop the land now ?
<START:person> Paladino <END> said the return of young people and empty-nesters to cities like <START:location> Buffalo <END> triggered the planned development .
“The market has improved for residential development .
It’s fairly good right now for apartments , ” <START:person> Paladino <END> said .
“Young people – and it ’s just a trend thing – they’ve had it with … mowing lawns and all that .
They want the urban life they see on TV , and to live approximate to things . ”
<START:person> Paladino <END> said he hopes the mostly vacant <START:organization> Commodore Perry <END> housing complex nearby will eventually be torn down .
“We’re just praying that they don’t rehab those apartments and put people back in them .
Hopefully , they will get rid of the whole thing and tear it down .
That <START:location> Perry Street <END> has caused a lack of interest in any development there . ”
<START:person> Paladino’s <END> plan to erect an office building follows this year’s $ 1 million remediation of the contaminated land where a gas station stood .
“We’re planning a nice two - or three-story building – how big depends on the tenants .
We first have to solidify the tenancy , and then it ’s likely we’ll start as soon as possible , ” <START:person> Paladino <END> said .
The <START:organization> Buffalo Scholastic Rowing Association <END> ’s new <START:organization> Patrick Paladino Memorial Boathouse <END> – named for <START:person> Carl Paladino’s <END> late son – is being built on land the developer leases to the group .
The boathouse property is just south of <START:person> Paladino’s <END> planned residential development , across from Father Conway Park .
While pleased that improvements were made to <START:location> Ohio Street <END> , <START:person> Paladino <END> criticized the decision to make it two lanes .
“They made a big mistake by making it into a two-way highway when it should have been a four-lane .
It’s a terrible mistake .
You can’t park a car .
And if you’re on it and stuck in traffic , you can’t even turn around .
And they’re talking about it being one of the feeders to the <START:location> Outer Harbor <END> , ” <START:person> Paladino <END> said .
But he reserved most of his ire for the bicycle lane .
“How many people are riding bikes in this community ?
For four or five months a year you can’t ride a bike in the snow .
If you want to ride a bike , do it on the sidewalk .
That’s why they have sidewalks , ” he said .
<START:person> Savarino’s <END> project , named <START:organization> Buffalo River Landing <END> , calls for covered parking on the property’s ground level , with housing units on the next four levels , including two office spaces on the second floor .
<START:person> Savarino <END> plans to salvage timber from the <START:organization> Erie Freight House <END> , if possible , to be used for decorative purposes , with iron beams refastened as exterior benches .
Corten steel would be used with masonry and translucent panels for the stairways to mimic some of the industrial architecture around the river’s edge , he said .
The original foundation would be kept as a promenade .
A patio and green space are planned between the building and the water .
<START:person> Savarino <END> said units would cost up to $ 2,700 a month for a large two-bedroom corner unit with a rooftop porch , with the lowest-priced apartments renting for around $ 800 .
He remains open to allowing the units to become condominiums in the future .
The leases would give tenants the option of keeping the unit should that happen .
He said he’s anxious to get started .
“People say to us that it ’s exciting that there are developments in <START:location> Buffalo <END> that are taking advantage of our location by the water , ” <START:person> Savarino <END> said .
“You don’t see enough of that . ”
