
First came <START:organization> AMC <END> 's <START:organization> Mad Men <END> , whose brown <START:organization> Frigidaires <END> and <START:organization> Eero Saarinen <END> tables helped ignite a craze for everything midcentury , modern , and whiskey-spiked .
Now <START:person> Amanda Kolson Hurley <END> writes for <START:organization> City Lab <END> that <START:organization> BBC America <END> 's <START:organization> The Game <END> is poised to do the same for <START:organization> Brutalism <END> .
In the spy thriller , " surprisingly intimate " concrete rooms are practically characters in and of themselves .
The spy HQ , what with its "rough , ribbed-concrete walls , " takes the harshest parts of the style and inhabits it with real human being feelings again .
What 's more , the building is actually home to the good guys rather than sociopaths .
Here a Brutalist icon serves as the hub for a bunch of well-dressed folk fighting for Queen and country .
As <START:person> Hurley <END> writes , "it makes Brutalism the scene of interactions that for once are n't thuggish or sinister . "
[ <START:organization> City Lab <END> ]

· Curbed Features archive [Curbed ]

Photo by <START:person> Maxime Brouillet <END> via <START:organization> Dwell <END>
In the hands of Canadian firm <START:organization> La SHED Architecture <END> , a dreary , well-worn duplex in <START:location> Montreal <END> is now completely unrecognizable .
Gone are the odd wallpaper and aged furnishings : after a massive renovation last year , the 2,700-square-foot home is all about bright lighting , vibrant colors , and versatile spaces .
As <START:organization> Dwell <END> notes , the architects only preserved the building 's "overall shape and footprint . "
Otherwise , the changes are drastic .
A new open-plan area for the kitchen and double-height living room has been opened up , with a home office hovering on the mezzanine above .
The kitchen has been recast in white lacquer and outfitted with stainless-steel countertops .
Standing out in the whole space is the intense orange-lacquer staircase right by the steel bookshelves .
Other transformations include the master bath , where a larger skylight showers the polished space with natural light , as well as the new patio carved out from the middle of the second floor .
Of course , with a budget of $ 400K , which is what was reported on the project page , this sort of extreme makeover is to be expected .
Here are some before-and-afters of the house 's kitchen , master bath , and rear .
Before :
Photo by <START:organization> La Shed Architecture <END> via <START:organization> Facebook <END>
After :
Photo by <START:person> Maxime Brouillet <END> via <START:organization> Dwell <END>
Before :
Photo by <START:organization> La Shed Architecture <END> via <START:organization> Facebook <END>
After :
Photo by <START:person> Maxime Brouillet <END> via <START:organization> Dwell <END>
Before :
Photo by <START:organization> La Shed Architecture <END> via <START:organization> Facebook <END>
After :
Photo by <START:person> Maxime Brouillet <END> via <START:organization> Dwell <END>
· A Concrete and Glass Home Frames Epic Views of <START:location> San Diego <END> <START:organization> [Dwell <END> ] · All <START:organization> La Shed Architecture <END> posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ] · All Renovations posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ] · All Extreme Makeovers posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ]

Photo by <START:person> Brian Nieblas <END>
Back in September , a deeply Ft .
Lauderdale spectacle by the name of <START:location> Le Palais Royal <END> hopped on the market at a staggering $ 139M , instantly becoming <START:location> America <END> 's most expensive home for sale .
Since then , the yet-to-be-completed megamansion has been dethroned by an $ 195M Beverly Hills compound and is now the country 's third most expensive listing , right behind the $ 140M <START:location> Hamptons <END> pad that listed last month .
Now , a fresh batch of construction photos show that , to the horror of <START:organization> Curbed <END> commenters who deemed the property " the Titanic of mansions , " a "pulsating nightmare , " an "architecturally bastardized mess , " the home is coming along exactly as promised by the initial renderings .
Expected to be completed next summer , the 60,000-square-foot palace will offer 11 bedrooms , a 492-foot private dock , an underground garage for over 30 cars , " the first-ever <START:organization> IMAX <END> Theater contracted for private use , " and a $ 2M marble staircase—the enticing makings of a property that , according to listing agent <START:person> William Pierce <END> , has attracted " a great deal of interest " from buyers around the world .
Below , new construction photos , plus an updated set of interior and exterior renderings .
· <START:location> 935 Hillsboro Mile <END> <START:organization> [Coldwell Banker <END> ] · $ 139M <START:location> Florida <END> Spectacle is America 's Most Expensive Listing ( now third most expensive ) <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ] · All Blockbusters posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ]

Is this space "feminine " ?
How about "ladylike " ?
Photo via <START:organization> Design Sponge <END>
Others have made the point before , but the ongoing use of the words "masculine " and "feminine " in design writing has us , the staff of <START:organization> Curbed National <END> , feeling it needs to be stated again , as clearly as possible : the people who write about decor and design need to stop describing spaces with gendered terms .
It 's an easy fix .
Decor bloggers , shelter editors , design writers : do n't type the words "masculine " or "manly " or "feminine " or "ladylike " or "girly " when describing spaces .
Do n't use any other words that prescribe gender to furniture or interiors .
Let 's say two spaces were written up in a decor blog , and one was described as masculine , and the other feminine .
Which would have white walls ?
Which would have raw concrete floors ?
Which would remind you more of <START:organization> Pinterest <END> ?
Which would have more heavy leather furniture ?
In which would the books be ordered by color , and what would that say about the person who organized them that way ?
Which would have more antlers and dark throws ?
If these have fairly easy answers , it 's because we 're in the realm of stereotype .
The uncharitable term for a writer who channels stereotypes without some measure of ironic distance is "hack . "
<START:organization> Curbed National <END> writers have used these terms before .
<START:organization> Curbed National <END> writers have stopped .
A room "masculine " enough for a modern lumberjack .
Photo via <START:organization> Urban Cowboy <END>
The use of the words "masculine " and "feminine " to describe spaces harks back to one of the very first lessons children learn in school ; what boys do and what girls do .
This is one of those parts of culture that it 's very good to train yourself out of , or be trained out of , or never learn in the first place .
Many people across the spectrum of gender and sexuality have complicated relationships with what society seems to expect from them .
It would be cool if these people could engage in the leisurely practice of reading about furniture or interiors without having some of the shallowest of those expectations foisted upon them .
It 's important to note that femininity , by and large , is considered an additive .
In interior design , it 's translated to fresh flowers , stemware , and bed skirts .
It is ephemeral where masculinity is formidable .
It is whimsical where masculinity is utilitarian .
It is antiqued where masculinity is modern .
Lace and chintz exist only in "feminine " spaces .
If spareness and raw architecture are "masculine , " then we 're essentially saying that traditionally "feminine " decorating is frivolous .
Suddenly those who associate themselves with femininity become a little less essential and a little less relevant .
And , in the end , maybe just a little less .
Who wants to live in a world where all of that is taken for granted ?
Some might , but why would we trust those people to advise us in matters of style ?
It 's laughable in an era where the most prominent proponent of pink in the world of industrial design is a man , and the most sought-after and vilified hero-architect in the world is a woman .
Gendered design writing is lazily offensive .
But more to the point , it 's offensively lazy .
We can do better .

Turns out it 's a bit tricky to translate the bohemian-modern design blog aesthetic ( that is natural , haphazard minimalism ) into holiday cheer .
Sometimes , in fact , the results are just downright chilling .
Here now , 10 examples of minimalist holiday decor ideas that took a turn for the depressing .
↑ Lonely .
[ link ]
↑ Dejected .
[ link ]
↑ Gloomy .
[ link ]
↑ Somber .
[ link ]
↑ Bleak .
[ link ]
↑ Mournful .
[ link ]
↑ Desperate .
[ link ]
↑ Sad .
[ link ]
↑ Distressing .
[ link ]
↑ Heartbreaking .
[ link ]
· All Holiday Trimmings posts <START:organization> [Curbed National <END> ]

Have a nomination for a jaw-dropping listing that would make a mighty fine House of the Day ? Get thee to the tipline and send us your suggestions .
We 'd love to see what you 've got .
Location : <START:location> Mint Hill , North Carolina <END> Price : $ 350K The Skinny : In <START:location> Mint Hill , North Carolina <END> , a pleasantly restored "turn of the century charmer " is on the market for a slightly reduced $ 350K.
Standout original details include diamond-pane windows , victorian doors , and tongue-and-groove wood-paneled walls and ceilings , whose historic integrity has been kept intact with " no expense spared . "
Electrical and plumbing systems have been brought up to date , as has the kitchen , which is reached through a beautiful set of sliding barn doors , and is apparently fit for a " chef/entertainer . "
There 's also a generous wraparound porch , and a detach two-car garage with a workshop area and upstairs storage .
· <START:location> 4122 Hoodridge Lane <END> <START:organization> [Zillow <END> ]

Photo via <START:organization> Wikipedia <END>
Following in the footsteps of the <START:organization> Museum of Modern Art <END> and the <START:organization> Frick Collection <END> , both of which have big expansions in the works , <START:location> New York City <END> 's renowned <START:organization> American Museum of Natural History <END> has also just announced plans for a major addition to its landmarked campus on the <START:location> Upper West Side <END> .
The new <START:organization> Richard Gilder Center for Science , Education , and Innovation <END> , intended to be completed in time for the museum 's 150th anniversary in 2019 , will be designed by starchitect <START:person> Jeanne Gang <END> , who most recently unveiled a provocative installation on climate change in <START:location> Miami <END> .
Adding 180,000 square feet of new space to existing museum space , the $ 325M project will dedicate altogether 218,000 square feet to science-focused exhibitions , labs , and theaters .
As <START:organization> Curbed NY <END> comments , backlash to the project is certain , considering current controversy over a church-to-condo conversion in the same neighborhood .
Stay tuned .
[ <START:organization> ArchDaily <END> ]

Have a nomination for a jaw-dropping listing that would make a mighty fine House of the Day ? Get thee to the tipline and send us your suggestions .
We 'd love to see what you 've got .
Location : <START:location> West Lake Hills , Texas <END> Price : $ 6,500,000 The Skinny : Architect <START:person> Winn Wittman <END> once called the 6,100-square-foot <START:location> Soaring Wings <END> house of <START:location> West Lake Hills , Texas <END> , the project that "literally almost killed me . "
While managing the four-year construction of the home , which wrapped up in 2007 , he fell off a rock wall and broke his back .
<START:person> Wittman <END> made a full recovery , and his work payed off pretty quickly , when the house sold just three months after completion .
" Our plan was to build our own home , " one of the buyers told <START:organization> Architectural Record <END> , " but when I walked in this one I felt spiritually connected to it instantly .
The quality and the craftsmanship are so high , and so specific , it seemed absurd that it was a spec house . "
Located just a short drive from downtown <START:location> Austin <END> , the home is connected to the locale by 45,000 pounds of red iron and 17,000 pounds of locally quarried shellstone .
( Other materials include pink <START:location> Arizona <END> sandstone , ipe wood , hand-seamed copper panels , and a " special concrete mixed with orange slice candy and gummi bears . " )
A two-story glass-and-steel bridge connects the four-bedroom private volume to the public one , which contains living , dining , and entertaining spaces .
Listed for $ 6.5M , it also comes with a saltwater pool , a long list of energy-saving features , a wine cellar , and a 3,200 pound granite bath tub .
Also , according to the listing , part of <START:person> Terrance Malick <END> 's upcoming film <START:organization> Knight of Cups <END> was shot inside .
· <START:location> 202 Red Bud Trail <END> [ <START:organization> Keller Williams <END> ]

<START:location> HONG KONG <END> — At least one thing caught the eye of <START:location> China’s <END> Internet czar during his trip to the <START:location> United States <END> last week : a book written by and about the president of <START:location> China <END> on the desk of <START:person> Mark Zuckerberg <END> .
<START:person> Mr. Zuckerberg <END> , the chief executive of <START:organization> Facebook <END> , pointed to the book , “ <START:person> Xi Jinping <END> : The Governance of <START:organization> China <END> ” last week while giving a tour of the company ’s office to <START:person> Lu Wei <END> , the de facto head of Internet policy in <START:location> China <END> .
<START:person> Mr. Lu <END> laughed when he saw the book , an anthology of speeches and comments by <START:person> President Xi <END> .
He then asked to sit down at <START:person> Mr. Zuckerberg’s <END> desk to have a closer look , according to an account published on a Chinese state-run website .
The interaction was confirmed by a person close to the traveling group who asked not to be identified because the meeting was private .
<START:organization> Facebook <END> is typically blocked in <START:location> China <END>  .
<START:person> Mr. Lu <END> , as <START:location> China’s <END> new Internet czar , holds the key for American Internet companies to the enormous Chinese market .
He is also the ambassador of an assertive new policy in which <START:location> China <END> claims the right to block websites , censor content and track users within its borders .
One photo taken of the <START:organization> Facebook <END> visit and posted on a site associated with <START:location> China’s <END> <START:organization> State Council Information office <END> shows <START:person> Mr. Lu <END> smiling as he looks down at the book .
Sporting a white cover with a painted image of <START:person> Mr. Xi’s <END> bust reminiscent of the famed portrait of <START:person> Mao Zedong <END> that hangs in <START:location> Tiananmen Square <END> , the text offered <START:person> Mr. Lu, <END> a longtime propagandist who rose through the ranks of <START:location> China’s <END> state-run <START:organization> Xinhua News Agency <END> , an easy conversation piece .
The book runs to 515 pages in English .
With the exception of a generous number of photos depicting Mr. Xi throughout his life , it might make tough reading , even for <START:organization> Communist Party <END> stalwarts .
<START:person> Mr. Zuckerberg <END> said he had bought the book for himself and co-workers to ensure that they “understood socialism with Chinese characteristics . ”
The book might give some <START:organization> Facebook <END> users pause , since the text includes a speech by <START:person> Mr. Xi <END> in which he says <START:location> Beijing <END> should “use Internet communication rules to advocate things wholesome and positive , and disseminate and put into practice the core socialist values , ” and “should properly handle timing , extent and efficiency to make our cyberspace wholesome and clean . ”
He also says , “It is a long-term task to ensure that online public opinion is healthy and sound . ”
The visit to <START:organization> Facebook <END> was part of a whirlwind tour in the <START:location> United States <END> for <START:person> Mr. Lu <END> , a trip that offered the contrast of coasts .
In <START:location> Washington <END> , <START:person> Mr. Lu <END> faced strong criticism from American officials over Chinese hacking attacks and skepticism about his vision for Internet governance .
On the <START:location> West Coast <END> , though , he received a warmer welcome from technology executives , including <START:person> Jeff Bezos <END> , chief executive of <START:organization> Amazon <END> , and <START:person> Timothy D. Cook <END> , the head of <START:organization> Apple. <END>
<START:person> Mr. Lu’s <END> trip was followed closely in the Chinese news media ; in one broadcast on the <START:location> Hong Kong <END> -based <START:organization> Phoenix Television <END> , <START:organization> eBay’s <END> chief executive , <START:person> John Donahoe <END> , was shown discussing how crucial Chinese merchants were to the company .
Responding to reports of <START:person> Mr. Zuckerberg’s <END> meeting and his reference to <START:person> Mr. Xi’s <END> book , <START:person> Hu Jia <END> , a Chinese activist , said on Monday in a <START:organization> Twitter <END> post that <START:organization> Facebook <END> was “ risking repeating the mistakes of <START:organization> Yahoo <END> ” by becoming too close to the <START:organization> Chinese government <END> .
In 2004 , the Chinese journalist <START:person> Shi Tao <END> was arrested by Chinese officials after <START:organization> Yahoo <END> provided information about his account to the government .
The episode prompted <START:organization> Yahoo's <END> co-founder , <START:person> Jerry Yang <END> , to apologize to <START:person> Mr. Shi’s <END> family .
<START:person> Mr. Shi <END> served a prison sentence from 2005 to 2013 .
<START:organization> Facebook <END> did not respond to an email seeking comment on <START:person> Mr. Lu’s <END> visit to the company .
The Chinese Internet market is huge .
A recent report by the research company <START:organization> IDC <END> projected that with more than 680 million people expected to be online in <START:location> China <END> next year , its market will account for 43 percent of worldwide growth in the technology sector .
That makes it an increasingly important place to be for American companies .
But strict barriers and regulations in <START:location> China <END>  keep many of them at arm’s length .
<START:organization> Linked In <END> , the professional social network , has decided to censor some content on its Chinese site .
<START:organization> Apple <END> has agreed to host some data within <START:location> China’s <END> borders , where Chinese officials could potentially gain access to it , and this year it put out a job advertisement for a head of law enforcement in the country .
The job posting read in part : “The role will be directly responsible for the management , handling and issuance of appropriate responses to requests from law enforcement authorities , public prosecutors and courts etc . throughout <START:location> China <END> . ”
During <START:person> Mr. Lu’s <END> visit in <START:location> Washington <END> , he met with members of the <START:organization> National Security Council <END> , who criticized continuing hackings against American companies and <START:location> China’s <END> top-down , government-led approach to managing the Internet , according to a senior American administration official who spoke on the condition that he not be named because the meetings were confidential .
The disagreement between the United States and <START:location> China <END> on such critical issues may provide one answer to why Mr. Lu gave equal emphasis to the <START:location> East Coast <END> and <START:location> West Coast <END> on his trip to the <START:location> United States. <END>
Meeting with <START:location> United States <END> technology companies provided <START:person> Mr. Lu <END> with ample photo opportunities to show off back home .
It also demonstrated that he could easily find eager partners in <START:location> Silicon Valley <END> , even as officials in <START:location> Washington <END> seek to play hardball .
<START:person> Jane Perlez <END> contributed reporting .

<START:person> Loc Tran <END> is a big man on campus at <START:organization> San Jose State University <END> in <START:location> Northern California <END> .
“A lot of people stop me when I’m walking , ” said <START:person> Mr. Tran <END> , a 19-year-old sophomore , who speaks in quick and confident bursts .
“They congratulate me . ”
But <START:person> Mr. Tran <END> is not a star on the football team , or a leader in student government .
He is a top player on the school’s competitive video game team , helping <START:organization> San Jose State <END> claw its way to victory in June over <START:organization> California State University , Fullerton <END> , in a tournament watched online by nearly 90,000 people .
When the new school year started this fall , classmates ’ heads swiveled toward him when professors said his name during roll call .
“ I thought that was pretty cool , ” <START:person> Mr. Tran <END> said .
Video game competitions , also known as e-sports , have taken off on campuses across the country , including <START:organization> Harvard <END> and <START:organization> Florida State University <END> .
More than 10,000 students now play in the biggest college league , 4,400 more than last year and 4,600 more than the number of men who play on Division I college basketball teams .
The stakes keep climbing , too : Winning a big tournament can sometimes earn players several years ’ worth of tuition money .
And in a possible sign of the future , the athletic department of <START:organization> Robert Morris University Illinois <END> in <START:location> Chicago <END> created an official video game team this fall , offering the same sort of scholarships given to athletes playing soccer , football and ice hockey .
While the college e-sports craze started as a grass-roots effort , game makers have quickly swooped in , propelling the sharp rise in interest .
The companies now underwrite scholarship prizes , offer team banners and provide organizational support , sensing a possible breeding ground for a new generation of superfans — people who not only play games but also consider them a spectator sport .
“Game developers are really waking up to the publicity power of these communities , ” said <START:person> T. L. Taylor <END> , an associate professor of comparative media studies at the <START:organization> Massachusetts Institute of Technology <END> , who has studied e-sports .
Colleges , meanwhile , are often standing at arm’s length .
While e-sports groups are often sanctioned clubs , receiving practice spaces from their schools , the leagues and competitions have few of the student regulations governing traditional college sports , like grade-point minimums or time limits on practicing .
The rise in e-sports has been so abrupt , many schools have not determined what to make of it .
<START:person> Carter Henderson <END> , a spokesman for the <START:organization> University of Washington’s <END> athletics program , said no one from the department was familiar enough with e-sports to discuss the topic .
The <START:organization> National Collegiate Athletic Association <END> , which oversees college athletics , said it had no comment about e-sports on campus .
Game companies say it is too early to predict how university administrations will become involved in e-sports .
“This is just how basketball was in the 1940s , ” said <START:person> Christopher Wyatt <END> , senior manager for North American publishing at <START:organization> Riot Games <END> .
“A lot of the structure and organization you see in more formal athletics , that groundwork is still being laid down here . ”
But it is unclear whether becoming a more formal part of a school would help or harm the growth of college e-sports .
The time commitment required for serious competitive gaming could lead to concerns about whether e-sports leave enough time for academic study .
In addition , formal recognition could diminish the autonomy that companies and teams have on campuses , bringing about rules like Title IX , the gender equity law .
About the possibility of more official recognition , <START:person> Dr. Taylor <END> said , “ I don’t think collegiate e-sports players are unified in any way that this is a good thing . ”
For game developers , however , the lure of being on campus is simple .
“We think that ’s where a lot of our players are , ” said <START:person> Michael Morhaime <END> , the chief executive and co-founder of <START:organization> Blizzard Entertainment <END> , which develops and publishes entertainment software .
In September , <START:organization> Blizzard <END> flew eight finalists from the <START:organization> College of Staten Island <END> , <START:organization> University of Massachusetts-Amherst <END> and other colleges to <START:location> Seattle <END> to compete for $ 5,000 in scholarship money in a tournament of <START:organization> Hearthstone <END> , a virtual card game from the company .
Last year , <START:organization> Azubu <END> , a games media company , sponsored a competition that awarded $ 40,000 in prize money to six students on a StarCraft II team from the <START:organization> University of California , Berkeley <END> .
Last February , <START:organization> Riot Games <END> hosted its first North American Collegiate Championship , something like the Final Four for <START:organization> League of Legends <END> , <START:organization> Riot’s <END> popular online battle game .
A team of five students from the <START:organization> University of Washington <END> won in front of a roaring audience at an e-sports studio that <START:organization> Riot <END> operates in <START:location> Manhattan Beach , Calif. <END> , with 169,000 more people watching online at the tournament’s peak .
The prize was $ 7,500 in scholarship money for each team member .
Riot recently announced that first-place winnings at the next championship , to be held in the spring , would rise to $ 30,000 , enough to pay for about three years of in-state tuition at the <START:organization> University of Washington. <END>
“A lot more people than I expected came forward and said , ‘I’d like to try out for the team , ’ ” said <START:person> Jackson Brown <END> , the manager of the <START:organization> University of Washington’s <END> team , the <START:organization> Purple Caster Minions <END> .
The growth of competitive gaming at colleges mirrors the broader rise of e-sports as entertainment .
A thriving international professional e-sports circuit routinely draws tens of thousands of spectators to stadiums for competitions , with millions more viewers online .
Top prizes for some events are now in the millions of dollars .
<START:organization> Twitch <END> , a video streaming service that made its name broadcasting e-sport matches , was acquired this year for close to $ 1 billion by <START:organization> Amazon <END> .
The college scene is largely organized around the <START:organization> Collegiate StarLeague <END> , which started at <START:organization> Princeton <END> in 2009 and is the biggest college league .
The organization is now active at 450 schools , up from 260 last year , according to <START:person> Duran Parsi <END> , the head of the league .
Many of those players also participate in matches organized by another collegiate league , <START:organization> IvyLoL <END> .
Large <START:location> West Coast <END> schools like the <START:organization> University of Washington <END> and <START:organization> University of British Columbia <END> tend to dominate the competitions .
The money that game companies are pouring into the college scene has persuaded many students to become much more serious about e-sports .
College scholarships from corporations , including <START:organization> Coca-Cola, <END> <START:organization> Ford <END> and <START:organization> Google <END> , have been around for decades , usually to encourage students to enter a particular field , like engineering .
The money that game companies are giving to students , in contrast , is meant to deepen the companies ’ relationship with a whole generation of players , one that is inseparable from their products .
Today , most professional players skip or delay college , because the college-age years are considered the prime period for players in the big leagues .
Playing at the professional level requires far too much time for practice and travel to tournaments to allow them to also attend school .
<START:person> Conan Liu <END> , a student at <START:organization> Berkeley <END> , took a year off from school to play StarCraft II professionally after his school team won the <START:organization> Azubu <END> championship .
<START:person> Mr. Liu <END> returned to school this fall to focus on pre-med studies because he did not perform as well as he had hoped in the pros .
While even bench warmers in the <START:organization> National Basketball Association <END> make more than $ 500,000 a year , the same is not true of professional gamers .
“You have to really be at the top , top to make a nice living , ” <START:person> Mr. Liu <END> said .
Game companies and collegiate league organizers predict that college e-sports could become a pipeline for the growing professional circuit .
Game companies say they are awarding scholarship money at college tournaments , rather than unrestricted cash prizes , to give students an incentive to continue their studies .
“We really want e-sports to become as ingrained in the academic environment as anything else — speech competitions , football competitions , ” said <START:person> Tyler Rosen <END> , president of the <START:organization> e-Sports Association <END> , which helps organize college events with the financial support of <START:organization> Blizzard Entertainment <END> .
A test of what happens when schools embrace e-sports started recently at <START:organization> Robert Morris University Illinois <END> .
The first 35 students to receive athletic scholarships under the school’s new e-sports program began training this fall in a room decked out with jet-black walls , mood lighting and leather gamer chairs with red piping .
The students , all <START:organization> League of Legends <END> players , are getting up to 50 percent of the price of tuition and room and board , which runs about $ 39,000 a year , according to <START:person> Kurt Melcher <END> , the university’s associate athletic director .
<START:person> Mr. Melcher <END> said he had received more than half a dozen calls from athletic directors at other universities who are interested in incorporating e-sports into their programs .
The idea came to <START:person> Mr. Melcher <END> , a gamer , this year after he started reading about the <START:organization> Collegiate StarLeague <END> .
A conversation with his wife dispelled any doubts he had about awarding athletic scholarships to gamers .
<START:person> Mr. Melcher <END> said his wife asked , “ Why should it only be given to some kid who can put a ball into a hole ? ”

<START:location> PARIS <END> — Europe wants to cash in on its tough data protection rules .
<START:organization> European Union <END> policy makers are demanding greater controls over how companies like <START:organization> Google <END> and <START:organization> Facebook <END> use personal information .
At the same time , others would like to use those same laws to help European companies compete against their American rivals as a way to jump-start a sluggish economy .
That debate over how best to leverage the regulations was on show during a meeting here on Monday , as local privacy regulators gathered to discuss the growing public outcry over how governments and tech giants gather and use people’s data .
That outcry has resulted from disclosures by <START:person> Edward J. Snowden <END> , the former <START:organization> National Security Agency <END> contractor , about the activities of the American and British intelligence services , as well as the expanding use of people’s information by Internet companies like <START:organization> Microsoft <END> and <START:organization> Amazon <END> .
‘‘ We feel we are losing control over our data , ’’ said <START:person> Isabelle Falque-Pierrotin <END> , who heads the French data protection authority .
‘‘Data protection is at a crossroads , and it ’s important that Europe speaks with one voice .’’
Europe is now completing a new round of privacy rules , expected to be made final next year , that will give greater power to individuals over who has access to their data and how it is used .
European policy makers are also considering fines of up to 5 percent of a company ’s annual revenue , or $ 125 million , whichever is greater , when the strict privacy rules are breached .
While regulators are pressing ahead with even tougher data protection rules , some of Europe’s lawmakers are eager to allow homegrown companies to use the rules governing the growing amount of personal information online as a defense against the American tech giants that currently dominate the region’s Internet economy .
In <START:location> Germany <END> , for example , policy makers and tech companies have created made-in-Germany email and cloud services — which allow people to store information on the Internet instead of on their own hard drives — that comply with the country ’s tough data protection rules .
And companies in <START:location> Finland <END> and <START:location> France <END> are pushing their own rival services , which are based on <START:location> Europe’s <END> stricter privacy rules , in the hope of enticing users to switch from American Internet giants to local competitors .
‘‘ <START:location> Europe <END> must turn data protection into a competitive advantage , ’’ <START:person> Manuel Valls <END> , the French prime minister , said at the meeting here on Monday .
‘‘It’s difficult to accept that European citizens have their data siphoned off by other countries without their knowledge .’’
Critics warn , however , that <START:location> Europe <END> must also beef up its oversight of all technology companies as they are increasingly scraping individual data for commercial use .
Currently , each of the <START:organization> European Union’s <END> 28 members has a separate data protection authority that oversees the activities of companies in its jurisdiction .
Campaigners say that these domestic regulators have yet to assess hefty fines on Internet companies for the potential abuse of people’s online data , and that the system must be revamped to keep up with how companies , either European or those from outside the union , are using online information .
‘‘The system we have now is n’t working , ’’ said <START:person> Max Schrems <END> , an Austrian lawyer who has brought a class-action lawsuit against <START:organization> Facebook <END> that accuses the company of misusing personal data .
‘‘If you park in the wrong place , you get a parking ticket .
But if a company violates the privacy rights of millions of people , nothing happens .’’

<START:organization> Google <END> , like many tech companies , is a man’s world .
Started by a pair of men , its executive team is overwhelmingly male , and its work force is dominated by men .
Over all , seven out of 10 people who work at <START:organization> Google <END> are male .
Men make up 83 percent of <START:organization> Google’s <END> engineering employees and 79 percent of its managers .
In a report to the <START:organization> Equal Employment Opportunity Commission <END> last year , <START:organization> Google <END> said that of its 36 executives and top-ranking managers , just three are women .
<START:organization> Google’s <END> leaders say they are unhappy about the firm’s poor gender diversity , and about the severe underrepresentation of blacks and Hispanics among its work force .
And so they are undertaking a long-term effort to improve these numbers , the centerpiece of which is a series of workshops aimed at making <START:organization> Google <END> ’s culture more accepting of diversity .
There’s just one problem : The company has no solid evidence that the workshops , or many of its other efforts to improve diversity , are actually working .
In some ways <START:organization> Google’s <END> plan to fix its diversity issues resembles many of its most ambitious product ideas , from self-driving cars to wiring the country for superfast Internet .
As in those efforts , it has set a high goal in this case : to fight deep-set cultural biases and an insidious frat-house attitude that pervades the tech business .
Tech luminaries make sexist comments so often that it has ceased to be news when they do .
<START:organization> Google <END> is attacking the problem with its considerable resources and creativity .
But it does not have a timeline for when the company ’s work force might become representative of the population , or whether it will ever get there .
“ I think it ’s terrific that they’re doing this , ” said <START:person> Freada Kapor Klein <END> , an entrepreneur who has long studied workplace diversity , and who is the co-chairwoman of the <START:organization> Kapor Center for Social Impact <END> .
“ But it ’s going to be important that <START:organization> Google <END> not just give a lecture about the science , but that there be active strategies on how to mitigate bias .
A one-shot intervention against a lifetime of biased messages is unlikely to be successful . ”
Google says its plan is n’t one-shot .
It points out that it has been trying to improve its diversity for years by sponsoring programs to increase the number of women and minorities who go into tech , and meticulously studying the way it hires people in an effort to reduce bias .
In May after pressure from civil rights leaders , the company published a report documenting the sex and race of its employees “to be candid about the issues , ” <START:person> Laszlo Bock <END> , <START:organization> Google’s <END> executive in charge of human resources , wrote at the time .
<START:organization> Google’s <END> disclosure prompted a wave of similar reports across the industry , with <START:organization> Facebook <END> , <START:organization> Apple <END> , <START:organization> Yahoo <END> and other tech giants issuing similarly dismal numbers about their work forces .
<START:organization> Google’s <END> diversity training workshops , which began last year and which more than half of <START:organization> Google <END> ’s nearly 49,000 employees have attended , are based on an emerging field of research in social psychology known as unconscious bias .
These are the hidden , reflexive preferences that shape most people’s worldviews , and that can profoundly affect how welcoming and open a workplace is to different people and ideas .
<START:organization> Google’s <END> interest in hidden biases was sparked in 2012 , when <START:person> Mr. Bock <END> read an article in <START:organization> The New York Times <END> about a study that showed systematic discrimination against female applicants for scientific jobs in academia .
The effect was so pervasive that researchers theorized the discrimination must be governed by unconscious cultural biases rather than overt sexism .
<START:person> Mr. Bock <END> wondered how such unconscious biases were playing out at <START:organization> Google <END> .
“This is a pretty genteel environment , and you don’t usually see outright manifestations of bias , ” he said .
“Occasionally you’ll have some idiot do something stupid and hurtful , and I like to fire those people . ”
But <START:person> Mr. Bock <END> suspected that the more pernicious bias was most likely pervasive and hidden , a deep-set part of the culture rather than the work of a few loudmouth sexists .
Improving diversity was n’t just a feel-good goal for <START:organization> Google <END> .
Citing research that shows diverse teams can be more creative than homogeneous ones , <START:person> Mr. Bock <END> argued that a diverse work force could be good for <START:organization> Google’s <END> business .
Could <START:organization> Google <END> investigate how biases were affecting people’s work — and , more important , could it change its own culture ?
Google’s human resources group , which goes by the name People Operations , functions like a graduate school research lab , with staff scientists who are constantly analyzing the company ’s internal operations .
<START:person> Mr. Bock <END> asked one of these researchers , <START:person> Brian Welle <END> , to begin a project on hidden biases .
After a few months , <START:person> Dr. Welle <END> came up with a 90-minute lecture targeted specifically at a skeptical , scientifically minded <START:organization> Google <END> employee .
The lecture begins with a dismal fact : Everyone is a little bit racist or sexist .
If you think you’re immune , take the Implicit Association Test , which empirically measures people’s biases .
<START:person> Dr. Welle <END> goes on to explain that some of the most damaging bias is unconscious ; people do the worst stuff without meaning to , or even recognizing that they’re being influenced by their preferences .
The effect of bias is powerful , and it is n’t softened by <START:location> Silicon Valley’s <END> supposedly meritocratic culture .
In the lecture , <START:person> Dr. Welle <END> shows a computer simulation of how a systematic 1 percent bias against women in performance evaluation scores can trickle up through the ranks , leading to a severe underrepresentation of women in management .
Finally , <START:person> Dr. Welle <END> points to research showing that we aren’t slaves to our hidden biases .
The more we make ourselves aware of the role our unconscious plays in our decision-making , and the more we try to force others to confront their biases , the greater the chance we have of overcoming our hidden preferences .
<START:organization> Google <END> offered several anecdotes that seem to indicate a less biased culture as a result of the training .
Not long ago the company opened a new building , and someone spotted the fact that all the conference rooms were named after male scientists ; in the past , that might have gone unmentioned , but this time the names were changed .
During one recent promotion meeting in which a group of male managers were deciding the fate of a female engineer , a senior manager who had been through the bias training cautioned his colleagues to remember that they were all men — and thus might not be able to fully appreciate the different roles women perform in engineering groups .
“ Just raising the awareness was enough for people to think about it , ” <START:person> Mr. Bock <END> said .
The woman was promoted .
Another time , in an all-company presentation , an interviewer asked a male and female manager who had recently begun sharing an office , “ Which one of you does the dishes ? ”
The strange , sexist undertone of the question was immediately seized upon by a senior executive in the crowd , who yelled , “ Unconscious bias ! ”
<START:person> Mr. Bock <END> saw all of these actions as evidence that the training was working .
“Suddenly you go from being completely oblivious to going , ‘Oh my god , it ’s everywhere , ’ ” he said .
But whether that will lead to a long-term change at <START:organization> Google <END> and , in turn , the rest of the tech industry , remains an open question .

<START:location> MOUNTAIN VIEW , Calif <END> .
— LAST June , in an interview with Adam Bryant of The Times , <START:person> Laszlo Bock <END> , the senior vice president of people operations for <START:organization> Google <END> — i .e . , the guy in charge of hiring for one of the world’s most successful companies — noted that <START:organization> Google <END> had determined that “G.P.A.’s are worthless as a criteria for hiring , and test scores are worthless .
... We found that they don’t predict anything . ”
He also noted that the “proportion of people without any college education at <START:organization> Google <END> has increased over time ” — now as high as 14 percent on some teams .
At a time when many people are asking , “How’s my kid gonna get a job ? ”
I thought it would be useful to visit <START:organization> Google <END> and hear how <START:person> Bock <END> would answer .
Don’t get him wrong , <START:person> Bock <END> begins , “Good grades certainly don’t hurt . ”
Many jobs at <START:organization> Google <END> require math , computing and coding skills , so if your good grades truly reflect skills in those areas that you can apply , it would be an advantage .
But <START:organization> Google <END> has its eyes on much more .
“There are five hiring attributes we have across the company , ” explained <START:person> Bock <END> .
“If it ’s a technical role , we assess your coding ability , and half the roles in the company are technical roles .
For every job , though , the No. 1 thing we look for is general cognitive ability , and it ’s not I.Q .
It’s learning ability .
It’s the ability to process on the fly .
It’s the ability to pull together disparate bits of information .
We assess that using structured behavioral interviews that we validate to make sure they’re predictive . ”
The second , he added , “is leadership — in particular emergent leadership as opposed to traditional leadership .
Traditional leadership is , were you president of the chess club ?
Were you vice president of sales ?
How quickly did you get there ?
We don’t care .
What we care about is , when faced with a problem and you’re a member of a team , do you , at the appropriate time , step in and lead .
And just as critically , do you step back and stop leading , do you let someone else ?
Because what’s critical to be an effective leader in this environment is you have to be willing to relinquish power . ”
What else ? Humility and ownership .
“It’s feeling the sense of responsibility , the sense of ownership , to step in , ” he said , to try to solve any problem — and the humility to step back and embrace the better ideas of others .
“Your end goal , ” explained <START:person> Bock <END> , “is what can we do together to problem-solve .
I’ve contributed my piece , and then I step back . ”
And it is not just humility in creating space for others to contribute , says <START:person> Bock <END> , it ’s “intellectual humility .
Without humility , you are unable to learn . ”
It is why research shows that many graduates from hotshot business schools plateau .
“Successful bright people rarely experience failure , and so they don’t learn how to learn from that failure , ” said <START:person> Bock <END> .
“They , instead , commit the fundamental attribution error , which is if something good happens , it ’s because I’m a genius .
If something bad happens , it ’s because someone’s an idiot or I did n’t get the resources or the market moved .
... What we’ve seen is that the people who are the most successful here , who we want to hire , will have a fierce position .
They’ll argue like hell .
They’ll be zealots about their point of view .
But then you say , ‘here’s a new fact , ’ and they’ll go , ‘ Oh , well , that changes things ; you’re right . ’
” You need a big ego and small ego in the same person at the same time .
The least important attribute they look for is “expertise . ”
Said <START:person> Bock <END> : “If you take somebody who has high cognitive ability , is innately curious , willing to learn and has emergent leadership skills , and you hire them as an H.R. person or finance person , and they have no content knowledge , and you compare them with someone who’s been doing just one thing and is a world expert , the expert will go : ‘I’ve seen this 100 times before ; here ’s what you do . ’ ” Most of the time the nonexpert will come up with the same answer , added <START:person> Bock <END> , “because most of the time it ’s not that hard . ”
Sure , once in a while they will mess it up , he said , but once in a while they’ll also come up with an answer that is totally new .
And there is huge value in that .
To sum up <START:person> Bock’s <END> approach to hiring : Talent can come in so many different forms and be built in so many nontraditional ways today , hiring officers have to be alive to every one — besides brand-name colleges .
Because “when you look at people who don’t go to school and make their way in the world , those are exceptional human beings .
And we should do everything we can to find those people . ”
Too many colleges , he added , “don’t deliver on what they promise .
You generate a ton of debt , you don’t learn the most useful things for your life .
It’s [just ] an extended adolescence . ”
<START:organization> Google <END> attracts so much talent it can afford to look beyond traditional metrics , like G.P.A.
For most young people , though , going to college and doing well is still the best way to master the tools needed for many careers .
But <START:person> Bock <END> is saying something important to them , too : Beware .
Your degree is not a proxy for your ability to do any job .
The world only cares about — and pays off on — what you can do with what you know ( and it does n’t care how you learned it ) .
And in an age when innovation is increasingly a group endeavor , it also cares about a lot of soft skills — leadership , humility , collaboration , adaptability and loving to learn and re-learn .
This will be true no matter where you go to work .

Once upon a time , a new technology happened along .
It was called radio .
Soon enough , some people began plucking wireless transmissions out of the air for their own purposes .
One clever young man in <START:location> Washington <END> figured out how to intercept messages that <START:organization> Navy <END> units sent to one another .
“ He has represented himself to be at distant naval stations or at sea on warships equipped with wireless apparatus , ” a magazine called <START:organization> Electrical World <END> reported in 1907 .
Back then , this fellow’s actions were not unlawful .
They amounted nonetheless to a form of piracy .
As radio grew more sophisticated , so did those intent on beating the system .
In 1960s <START:location> Britain <END> , radio pirates flourished on unlicensed stations that broadcast from ships anchored beyond territorial limits .
They found eager audiences in young people who tuned in for the latest from the <START:organization> Rolling Stones <END> , <START:organization> the Kinks <END> and <START:organization> the Who <END> .
( Talkin’ ′bout my generation . )
Then the world went digital .
Naturally , pirates tagged along .
One of them , the online sharing service <START:organization> Napster <END> , forms the core of this <START:organization> Retro Report <END> offering , the final installment in the current series of video documentaries examining the consequences of major news stories from the past .
<START:organization> Napster <END> did not last long , two years .
But for a while at the dawn of this century it claimed to have 70 million registered users .
It spawned a host of Internet music-swapping providers , more than a few of them falling on the dubious side of the law .
Most important , it irrevocably altered not only the way in which Americans absorbed music but also their belief system in what they should pay .
The conviction theologically held by many boiled down to a single word : nothing .
“You have a generation of people now who expect their music for free , ” <START:person> Greg Hammer <END> , managing director of <START:organization> Red Bull Records <END> , a branch of the energy-drink company , told <START:organization> Retro Report <END> .
“It’s very difficult to change . ”
The music industry is not alone in coming to terms with altered realities .
As every sentient soul surely knows by now , the “culture of free” — words borrowed from the title of this week’s video — has turned the print world upside down , pushing newspapers , magazines and book publishers into a frantic search for financial safe harbors .
With the advent of broad Internet use in the 1990s came a notion that information should be free .
Never mind that the gathering and transmission of information can be a costly proposition and that ( dirty word alert ) money is needed if the survival of , say , a newspaper is to be ensured .
As with music in <START:person> Mr. Hammer’s <END> observation , a generation now believes that the written word , whether on processed wood or in pixels , should come without charge .
<START:organization> Napster <END> burst forth in June 1999 , the brainchild of an entrepreneurial , 18-year-old computer wiz , <START:person> Shawn Fanning <END> .
His creation enabled anyone with a modicum of tech savvy to share audio files in MP3 format — peer to peer , as it was called .
Music lovers could download thousands upon thousands of songs , then pass them on to friends or create albums of their own on compact discs .
No one paid royalties .
To music companies and some individual artists , this was high-tech piracy and a threat to their fiscal well-being .
( It might be noted that the commercial introduction of CDs in the early 1980s delivered its own near-mortal blow to an earlier technology , long-playing vinyl records . )
The <START:organization> Recording Industry Association of America <END> sued <START:organization> Napster <END> for copyright infringement .
So did a few musicians , like the rapper Dr. Dre and the heavy metal band <START:organization> Metallica <END> .
Not every performer thought of <START:organization> Napster <END> as the enemy .
Some who might otherwise have been doomed to oblivion regarded the service as a platform from which they might find listeners and build a fan base .
Nor were all economists convinced that one free download equaled one less sale of a high-priced CD ; quite possibly , some of them said , people were plugging into music that they would never have paid for .
<START:organization> Napster <END> , however , did not have the courts on its side .
Ordered by federal judges to stop allowing copyrighted material to be traded on its system , it shut down in July 2001 .
But from its ashes other file-sharing services arose , some bearing curious names like <START:organization> Grokster <END> , <START:organization> Kazaa <END> and <START:organization> Gnutella <END> .
<START:person> Mr. Fanning <END> tried his hand at new digital media endeavors , including Snocap and <START:organization> Napster <END> 2.0.
Few of those companies were unqualified successes .
One thing was certain , though : The culture of free was not going away .
A decade ago , <START:organization> Apple <END> established a new order in the commercial music universe by introducing the <START:organization> iTunes <END> store .
From its vast digital warehouse , customers could buy any song they wished , typically for 99 cents .
The arrangement was perhaps not ideal for the recording companies and for many performers .
Among other things , music albums — fixtures since the ’60s and , in many instances , creative masterpieces — were becoming relics ; single-song listening ruled , whether through an iTunes purchase or snatched from the ether via file-swapping networks .
Still , for the industry , some money was better than none , and so an <START:organization> iTunes <END> reality beat a <START:organization> Napster <END> world .
Now the music business is in transition once more , reshaped by streaming services like <START:organization> YouTube <END> , Spotify and <START:organization> Pandora <END> .
Instead of owning songs , a listener can in effect borrow them from millions of titles made available by these operations .
A cultural shift seems well underway , with more and more consumers sensing they no longer need to possess certain physical items , like CDs or books .
A reliable Internet connection will do .
Unlike <START:organization> Napster <END> and the like , the streaming services are not engaged in piracy .
They are legally licensed , having paid music companies some money .
They themselves cash in by selling advertising or , increasingly , by offering subscriptions to customers interested in a commercial-free experience .
The results have been stark .
Data from <START:organization> Nielsen SoundScan <END> , a sales-tracking system , show that consumers in this country listened to 70 billion songs via streaming services in the first half of 2014 , an increase of 42 percent from the same period a year earlier .
Sales of albums , whether on CDs or through digital downloads , declined by 15 percent .
Downloads of individual tracks were down by 13 percent .
Embrace the change , <START:location> Silicon Valley <END> types say .
But even if one does , it comes at a cost .
As CDs fade from the scene , so do stores like <START:organization> Tower Records <END> .
Thousands of jobs are lost : workers who make the discs , wholesale buyers , salespeople , stockroom clerks , accountants and others .
Substitute work for them is not assured in the digital cosmos .
And , thus far , the people who create the music on which others build their fortunes often receive mere rivulets of reward .
Not everyone is a <START:person> Beyoncé <END> or a <START:person> Taylor Swift <END> ( who has removed her entire oeuvre from <START:organization> Spotify <END> to keep it behind a pay wall ) .
Many more musicians are like <START:person> Zoe Keating <END> , a cellist from <START:location> Northern California <END> who described her situation in detail last year .
Over a six-month period , <START:person> Ms. Keating’s <END> songs had been played on <START:organization> Pandora <END> more than 1.5 million times ; that earned her all of $ 1,652.74 .
She had 131,000 plays on <START:organization> Spotify <END> in 2012 .
She took home $ 547.71 , or less than half a penny per play .
Some industry executives insist that , over time , things will sort themselves out , including how to steer more money to performers .
Last month , for instance , <START:organization> YouTube <END> announced plans to generate revenue by giving its users an opportunity to pay a few dollars a month in return for extra features that are not available to those who click on songs at no charge .
Royalties to artists , in theory anyway , would thus rise .
In the meantime , some oldsters ( talkin’ ′bout my generation again ) may derive a measure of comfort from learning that vinyl albums still have life .
<START:organization> Nielsen SoundScan <END> reported four million sales of vinyl LPs in the first half of this year , a 40 percent increase from the same period in 2013 .
Go figure .
Hey , maybe you can get a copy of “Revolution 9” from the <START:organization> Beatles <END> ’ White Album , and check out for yourself if , when played backward on a turntable , it really does tell you that <START:person> Paul <END> is dead .

Until last year , when she became a planning consultant for a college in <START:location> Florida <END> , <START:person> Alison Barlow <END> traveled almost full time for an information technology company .
She was away as long as three weeks a month , making it home on weekends about half the time .
When a hotel stay at a <START:organization> Hampton Inn <END> in suburban <START:location> Omaha <END> was punctuated by a bout of flu , the staff made drugstore runs and brought her tea and crackers .
Knowing she would return soon , she would leave a bag behind with toiletries , workout wear and extra clothes .
“You don’t want to check luggage on an airplane , ” she said .
While staying at a <START:organization> Candlewood Suites <END> , she borrowed books and DVDs .
As hotels continue to add all manner of fees and executives look over their shoulders at <START:organization> Airbnb <END> and the sharing economy , they are increasingly telling guests to pack light and borrow items from them .
While loan programs are an accepted feature at luxury and full-service hotels , experts say that those hotels are now expanding their offerings to include bicycles , automobiles and running gear .
And hotels on a lower tier , like <START:organization> Candlewood Suites <END> , are starting their own programs .
“It’s reached all the way down from luxury to full-service hotels , and it ’s not unusual for select service , ” says <START:person> Bjorn Hanson <END> , professor at the <START:organization> Tisch Center for Hospitality and Tourism <END> at <START:organization> New York University <END> .
Some programs — like <START:organization> Kimpton Hotels <END> ’ Forgot It ? We’ve Got It ! — have been available for a decade .
They are drawing renewed attention because younger travelers are responding to hotels ’ attempts to create a relationship by going out of their way for guests .
<START:person> Bonnie Knutson <END> , a professor at <START:organization> Michigan State University’s <END> <START:organization> School of Hospitality Business <END> , said she saw an emphasis on choice , personalization and customization .
“Guests are saying , ‘ I only want to pay for what I want to use , ' ” she said .
The <START:organization> Kimpton <END> program offers a variety of small items and appliances , including chargers , hair dryers , extension cords and curling irons .
<START:organization> Hyatt Has It <END> was introduced in February 2013 with similar offerings .
“Before , travelers thought we did n’t offer any product other than a toothbrush , ” says <START:person> Kristine Rose <END> , vice president for brand experience at <START:organization> Hyatt <END> .
The program is aimed at the female traveler .
“Women tend to travel with a lot more things in their luggage , ” she said .
The program is offered under different names at all <START:organization> Hyatt <END> brands .
In addition to lending books and DVDs , <START:organization> Candlewood Suites <END> , an extended-stay division of the <START:organization> InterContinental Hotels Group <END> , introduced a <START:organization> Lending Locker <END> in 300 hotels in October 2013 .
The floor-to-ceiling enclosure provides items not typically found in guest rooms including fans , crockpots , dehumidifiers and office supplies .
<START:person> Robert Radomski <END> , vice president for brand management at <START:organization> I.H.G. <END> 's extended-stay brands , which include <START:organization> Candlewood Suites <END> , says the program creates a feeling of belonging for guests .
“It adds to their comfort , ” he said .
Some programs emphasize fitness .
<START:organization> Westin Hotels <END> introduced a Westin-New Balance equipment-lending program at more than 200 hotels in November 2012 .
The company estimates 30,000 guests a year participate .
<START:person> Peter Shankman <END> , an entrepreneur and author of the coming book “Zombie Loyalists ” was one .
Fourteen months ago , at a <START:organization> Westin <END> in <START:location> Atlanta <END> , he was up at 5 a.m. for a run before an early meeting .
After donning his shorts , he realized he forgot to pack running socks .
Expecting to run a 10-kilometer race three days later , he thought wearing dress socks for a seven-mile run that morning invited blisters .
The front desk staff offered him a free pair of running socks .
“They allowed me to continue on a schedule I preferred , which meant more to me than anything , ” he said .
Still , he has not traveled without his own equipment since .
A <START:organization> Westin <END> hotel typically charges $ 5 per stay for the socks , freshly laundered workout wear in a variety of sizes for both sexes , and sneakers that are cleaned and disinfected after each use .
The inner soles are changed monthly .
Fitness appeal takes different forms .
In July 2013 , <START:organization> Kimpton <END> , in partnership with Public , a <START:location> San Francisco <END> boutique bicycle and equipment company , introduced a fleet of Kimpton-branded bicycles that are free for guests to use .
Two to 10 bikes are available at 61 locations .
For guests who prefer four wheels , in March Loews introduced a chauffeur-driven car at five locations nationwide to take guests to nearby destinations .
Guests are responsible for their return transportation to the hotel .
At locations in <START:location> Miami <END> , <START:location> Hollywood <END> and <START:location> Santa Monica <END> , the hotels also offer free <START:organization> Fiat <END> loaner cars .
Even as loan programs can create greater loyalty and perhaps a willingness to pay a premium for a specific hotel , they have potential drawbacks , according to one expert , who sees the possibility that fewer guests will request items in the future , because of concerns about health and well-being .
“Some hotels may temporarily suspend these items as a precautionary response to protecting guest health and reducing liability , ” <START:person> Henry Harteveldt <END> , an analyst at <START:organization> Atmosphere Research Group <END> , wrote in an email .
For some guests , like <START:person> Ms. Barlow <END> , a preferred amenity is the ability to leave belongings behind .
<START:person> Mike DeFrino <END> , the chief operating officer at <START:organization> Kimpton Hotels <END> , said he had noticed at locations in <START:location> Cambridge , Mass. <END> , and <START:location> Cupertino , Calif. <END> , as many as 5 percent of guests are leaving bags behind .
“At <START:location> Cupertino <END> , they leave suits , ” he said .
“They don’t want to travel with blazers . ”
By accepting guest property for safekeeping , hotels run the risk of losing reputation and loyalty if something happens to it .
“The worst thing is to lose or misplace a guest item , ” <START:person> Mr. Hanson <END> said .
<START:person> Ms. Barlow <END> said she drew the line at leaving a laptop .
Still , even as her travel has abated , she said she missed staying long enough to establish a rapport with the hotel staff .
