Updated , 9:10 p.m. | <START:location> OAKLAND , Calif <END> .
— The lawyers fighting <START:organization> Apple <END> in a class-action lawsuit involving iPods have managed to do a few remarkable things : They persuaded a judge to bring a decade-old lawsuit to trial here last week , for one .
They even managed to drag the famous <START:person> Steve Jobs <END> into giving a videotaped testimony shortly before he died three years ago .
But they have one big problem : Their case has no plaintiff .
A federal judge on Monday disqualified the only remaining plaintiff in the case , <START:person> Marianna Rosen <END> of <START:location> New Jersey <END> , after <START:organization> Apple’s <END> lawyers successfully argued that she did not even buy any iPods for which she is seeking damages .
That argument also gave Apple an opening last week to ask <START:person> Yvonne Gonzalez Rogers <END> , the federal judge overseeing the case , to throw out the suit .
The judge , however , disagreed with <START:organization> Apple’s <END> argument that it was too late to add a new plaintiff .
She ordered the plaintiff lawyers to find one by Tuesday morning .
The judge appeared annoyed about the discrepancies with <START:person> Ms. Rosen’s <END> iPods and scolded the plaintiff lawyers for failing to do their homework .
Another plaintiff in the case dropped out last week .
“You’ve certainly created a problem on the plaintiffs ’ side , ” Judge <START:person> Gonzalez Rogers <END> said before reaching her decision .
The lawsuit , filed a decade ago , involves older iPods , which played only songs sold in the iTunes Store , or those downloaded from CDs — not music from competing stores .
The plaintiff lawyers represent consumers who say <START:organizationn> Apple <END> violated antitrust law because to keep their music , people had to stay with the iPod and buy higher-priced ones rather than cheaper , alternative music players .
For this , the plaintiff lawyers want <START:organization> Apple <END> to pay consumers at least $ 350 million in damages .
The lawyers suing Apple were busy over the weekend , filing papers about <START:person> Ms. Rosen’s <END> standing as a witness .
Last week , <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> testified that she had bought two iPods : an iPod Nano in the fall of 2007 and an iPod Touch in December 2008 .
Apple’s lawyer asked whether <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> kept receipts for her purchases .
<START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> said she probably did not have the paper receipts , but later said her iPod Touch was in her bag .
<START:organization> Apple’s <END> lawyers looked up the serial number of <START:person> Ms. Rosen’s <END> iPod Touch and found records showing it was bought in July 2009 .
The class action seeks damages for iPods bought from September 2006 to March 2009 .
So this iPod Touch missed the cutoff .
<START:organization> Apple’s <END> lawyers last Wednesday pointed out the discrepancy about <START:person> Ms. Rosen’s <END> iPod Touch in a letter to the judge .
They also raised similar concerns about the second plaintiff’s iPod purchases .
On Friday , the second plaintiff dropped out of the case , leaving <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> as the lone plaintiff .
<START:person> Ms. Rosen’s <END> lawyers then provided <START:organization> Apple <END> a receipt showing two iPod purchases made in September 2008 .
But <START:organization> Apple <END> pulled up its copy of the receipt for those iPods , which indicated they were bought by the <START:organization> Rosen Law Firm <END> , the firm owned by <START:person> Ms. Rosen’s <END> husband .
<START:organization> Apple’s <END> lawyers argued that these were not iPods bought directly by <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> , and therefore she could not claim injury .
Over the weekend , <START:person> Ms. Rosen’s <END> lawyers filed a letter including a declaration by <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> about the iPods .
In it , <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> said that on Sept. 11 , 2008 , she bought an iPod Touch — not the same one that she brought to court .
She also said that on the same day , she bought the iPod Nano .
In her declaration , <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> also said that she bought the iPods for her own use , not for her husband’s law firm .
But she said that she believed the credit card she used was issued in both her name and that of the family business , the <START:organization> Rosen Law Firm <END> , and that she was authorized to make personal purchases with it .
In summary , <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> amended her testimony , saying that she bought two iPods on the same day in September 2008 .
Despite that , the judge said late Monday that <START:person> Ms. Rosen <END> was inadequate to serve as a plaintiff .
<START:person> Bonny Sweeney <END> , the plaintiff’s lead attorney , told the judge that a number of people had approached her team over the weekend , asking to be considered as plaintiffs , and many had already been interviewed .
“Yes , we certainly have another plaintiff , ” she said .
