The <START:organization> Senate Banking Committee <END> plans to hold a hearing next week on ways to “protect the financial sector ” from cyberattacks , but for now there are no plans to have anyone from the financial services industry testify .
The hearing set for Wednesday will feature testimony from top officials of the <START:organization> Federal Bureau of Investigation <END> , the <START:organization> Secret Service <END> , the <START:organization> Treasury Department <END> , the <START:organization> Department of Homeland Security <END> and the <START:organization> Office of the Comptroller of the Currency <END> .
The banking committee is holding the hearing in the aftermath of this summer ’s big cyberattack at <START:organization> JPMorgan Chase <END> that compromised some account information of 83 million households and small businesses .
Law enforcement officials have said the same hackers that breached <START:organization> JPMorgan’s <END> systems also tried to gain access to the systems of at least a dozen other financial institutions .
In October , the banking committee sent a letter to five regulators seeking information about how they were coordinating their work with law enforcement agencies in responding to attacks on the financial system .
They were also asked whether legislative proposals were needed to foster a better working relationship .
The letter specifically noted the attack on <START:organization> JPMorgan <END> and the need to make sure that government agencies the private institutions work together to maintain the “integrity of the financial system . ”
A person briefed on the matter said the hearing would focus on how the various government agencies were working together to deal with cyberattacks on banks and other financial institutions .
It’s not clear how much of the testimony will discuss the attack on JPMorgan or any other specific financial institution .
<START:person> Patricia Wexler <END> , a <START:organization> JPMorgan <END> spokeswoman , said the bank had not been asked to provide the committee with any information in advance of the hearing .
A spokeswoman for the <START:location> Connecticut <END> attorney general , <START:person> George Jepsen <END> , whose office is overseeing an investigation by several state attorneys generals into the <START:organization> JPMorgan <END> breach , said the state office had not been contacted by the <START:organization> Senate <END> committee .
In the <START:organization> JPMorgan <END> attack , the bank has said it found no evidence of any fraud or misuse of customer information .
<START:organization> JPMorgan <END> said the hackers got access only to customer email addresses , homes addresses and phone numbers but nothing of a more sensitive nature like Social Security numbers .
Over the past several years , cyberattacks on financial institutions have become a matter of increasing concern for regulators who are worried about criminals getting access to sensitive customer financial information or looting accounts .
To date , the most serious attacks have taken place in retail , with hackers attempting to get access to credit card account number by breaching the systems at companies like <START:organization> Target <END> and <START:organization> Home Depot <END> .
