http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/16/upshot/as-robots-grow-smarter-american-workers-struggle-to-keep-up.html
A machine that administers sedatives recently began treating patients at a <START:location> Seattle <END> hospital .
At a <START:location> Silicon Valley <END> hotel , a bellhop robot delivers items to people’s rooms .
Last spring , a software algorithm wrote a breaking news article about an earthquake that The <START:organization> Los Angeles Times <END> published .
Although fears that technology will displace jobs are at least as old as the Luddites , there are signs that this time may really be different .
The technological breakthroughs of recent years — allowing machines to mimic the human mind — are enabling machines to do knowledge jobs and service jobs , in addition to factory and clerical work .
And over the same 15-year period that digital technology has inserted itself into nearly every aspect of life , the job market has fallen into a long malaise .
Even with the economy ’s recent improvement , the share of working-age adults who are working is substantially lower than a decade ago — and lower than any point in the 1990s .
Economists long argued that , just as buggy-makers gave way to car factories , technology would create as many jobs as it destroyed .
Now many are not so sure .
“This is n’t some hypothetical future possibility , ” he said .
“This is something that ’s emerging before us right now . ”
<START:person> Erik Brynjolfsson <END> , an economist at <START:organization> M.I.T. <END> , said , “This is the biggest challenge of our society for the next decade . ”
<START:person> Mr. Brynjolfsson <END> and other experts say they believe that society has a chance to meet the challenge in ways that will allow technology to be mostly a positive force .
In addition to making some jobs obsolete , new technologies have also long complemented people’s skills and enabled them to be more productive — as the Internet and word processing have for office workers or robotic surgery has for surgeons .
More productive workers , in turn , earn more money and produce goods and services that improve lives .
“It is literally the story of the economic development of the world over the last 200 years , ” said <START:person> Marc Andreessen <END> , a venture capitalist and an inventor of the web browser .
“ Just as most of us today have jobs that weren’t even invented 100 years ago , the same will be true 100 years from now . ”
Yet there is deep uncertainty about how the pattern will play out now , as two trends are interacting .
Artificial intelligence has become vastly more sophisticated in a short time , with machines now able to learn , not just follow programmed instructions , and to respond to human language and movement .
At the same time , the American work force has gained skills at a slower rate than in the past — and at a slower rate than in many other countries .
Younger Americans are closer to average among the residents of rich countries , and below average by some measures .
Clearly , many workers feel threatened by technology .
In a recent <START:organization> New York Times/CBS News/Kaiser Family Foundation <END> poll of Americans between the ages of 25 and 54 who were not working , 37 percent of those who said they wanted a job said technology was a reason they did not have one .
Even more — 46 percent — cited “lack of education or skills necessary for the jobs available . ”
Self-driving vehicles are an example of the crosscurrents .
They could put truck and taxi drivers out of work — or they could enable drivers to be more productive during the time they used to spend driving , which could earn them more money .
But for the happier outcome to happen , the drivers would need the skills to do new types of jobs .
The challenge is evident for white-collar jobs , too .
Ad sales agents and pilots are two jobs that the <START:organization> Bureau of Labor Statistics <END> projects will decline in number over the next decade .
Flying a plane is largely automated today and will become more so .
And at <START:organization> Google <END> , the biggest seller of online ads , software does much of the selling and placing of search ads , meaning there is much less need for salespeople .
There are certain human skills machines will probably never replicate , like common sense , adaptability and creativity , said <START:person> David Autor <END> , an economist at <START:organization> M.I.T. <END>
Even jobs that become automated often require human involvement , like doctors on standby to assist the automated anesthesiologist , called <START:organization> Sedasys <END> .
Elsewhere , though , machines are replacing certain jobs .
Telemarketers are among those most at risk , according to a recent study by <START:organization> Oxford University <END> professors .
They identified recreational therapists as the least endangered — and yet that judgment may prove premature .
Already , <START:organization> Microsoft’s <END> <START:organization> Kinect <END> can recognize a person’s movements and correct them while doing exercise or physical therapy .
Other fields could follow .
The inventors of facial recognition software from a <START:organization> University of California , San Diego <END> lab say it can estimate pain levels from children’s expressions and screen people for depression .
Machines are even learning to taste : The <START:location> Thai <END> government in September introduced a robot that determines whether Thai food tastes sufficiently authentic or whether it needs another squirt of fish sauce .
<START:organization> Watson <END> , the computer system built by <START:organization> IBM <END> that beat humans at <START:organization> Jeopardy <END> in 2011 , has since learned to do other human tasks .
This year , it began advising military veterans on complex life decisions like where to live and which insurance to buy . <START:organization> Watson <END> culls through documents for scientists and lawyers and creates new recipes for chefs .
Now <START:organization> IBM <END> is trying to teach <START:organization> Watson <END> emotional intelligence .
<START:organization> IBM <END> , like many tech companies , says <START:organization> Watson <END> is assisting people , not replacing them , and enabling them to be more productive in new types of jobs .
It will be years before we know what happens to the counselors , salespeople , chefs , paralegals and researchers whose jobs <START:organization> Watson <END> is learning to do .
Whether experts lean toward the more pessimistic view of new technology or the most optimistic one , many agree that the uncertainty is vast .
Not even the people who spend their days making and studying new technology say they understand the economic and societal effects of the new digital revolution .
When the <START:organization> University of Chicago <END> asked a panel of leading economist s about automation , 76 percent agreed that it had not historically decreased employment .
But when asked about the more recent past , they were less sanguine .
About 33 percent said technology was a central reason that median wages had been stagnant over the past decade , 20 percent said it was not and 29 percent were unsure .
Perhaps the most worrisome development is how poorly the job market is already functioning for many workers .
More than 16 percent of men between the ages of 25 and 54 are not working , up from 5 percent in the late 1960s ; 30 percent of women in this age group are not working , up from 25 percent in the late 1990s .
For those who are working , wage growth has been weak , while corporate profits have surged .
“We’re going to enter a world in which there’s more wealth and less need to work , ” <START:person> Mr. Brynjolfsson <END> said .
“That should be good news .
But if we just put it on autopilot , there’s no guarantee this will work out .”
Some say the nature of work will need to change .
<START:organization> Google’s <END> co-founder , <START:person> Larry Page <END> , recently suggested a four-day workweek , so as technology displaces jobs , more people can find employment .
Others believe the role of the public sector should expand , to help those struggling to find work .
Many point to education , in new technologies and in the skills that remain uniquely human , like creativity and judgment .
“The answer is surely not to try to stop technical change , ” <START:person> Mr. Summers <END> said , “but the answer is not to just suppose that everything’s going to be O.K. because the magic of the market will assure that ’s true . ”
