http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/09/business/hotels-let-guests-borrow-items-or-leave-them.html
Until last year , when she became a planning consultant for a college in <START:location> Florida <END> , <START:person> Alison Barlow <END> traveled almost full time for an information technology company .
She was away as long as three weeks a month , making it home on weekends about half the time .
When a hotel stay at a <START:organization> Hampton Inn <END> in suburban <START:location> Omaha <END> was punctuated by a bout of flu , the staff made drugstore runs and brought her tea and crackers .
Knowing she would return soon , she would leave a bag behind with toiletries , workout wear and extra clothes .
“You don’t want to check luggage on an airplane , ” she said .
While staying at a <START:organization> Candlewood Suites <END> , she borrowed books and DVDs .
As hotels continue to add all manner of fees and executives look over their shoulders at <START:organization> Airbnb <END> and the sharing economy , they are increasingly telling guests to pack light and borrow items from them .
While loan programs are an accepted feature at luxury and full-service hotels , experts say that those hotels are now expanding their offerings to include bicycles , automobiles and running gear .
And hotels on a lower tier , like <START:organization> Candlewood Suites <END> , are starting their own programs .
“It’s reached all the way down from luxury to full-service hotels , and it ’s not unusual for select service , ” says <START:person> Bjorn Hanson <END> , professor at the <START:organization> Tisch Center for Hospitality and Tourism <END> at <START:organization> New York University <END> .
Some programs — like <START:organization> Kimpton Hotels <END> ’ Forgot It ? We’ve Got It ! — have been available for a decade .
They are drawing renewed attention because younger travelers are responding to hotels ’ attempts to create a relationship by going out of their way for guests .
<START:person> Bonnie Knutson <END> , a professor at <START:organization> Michigan State University’s <END> <START:organization> School of Hospitality Business <END> , said she saw an emphasis on choice , personalization and customization .
“Guests are saying , ‘ I only want to pay for what I want to use , ' ” she said .
The <START:organization> Kimpton <END> program offers a variety of small items and appliances , including chargers , hair dryers , extension cords and curling irons .
<START:organization> Hyatt Has It <END> was introduced in February 2013 with similar offerings .
“Before , travelers thought we did n’t offer any product other than a toothbrush , ” says <START:person> Kristine Rose <END> , vice president for brand experience at <START:organization> Hyatt <END> .
The program is aimed at the female traveler .
“Women tend to travel with a lot more things in their luggage , ” she said .
The program is offered under different names at all <START:organization> Hyatt <END> brands .
In addition to lending books and DVDs , <START:organization> Candlewood Suites <END> , an extended-stay division of the <START:organization> InterContinental Hotels Group <END> , introduced a <START:organization> Lending Locker <END> in 300 hotels in October 2013 .
The floor-to-ceiling enclosure provides items not typically found in guest rooms including fans , crockpots , dehumidifiers and office supplies .
<START:person> Robert Radomski <END> , vice president for brand management at <START:organization> I.H.G. <END> 's extended-stay brands , which include <START:organization> Candlewood Suites <END> , says the program creates a feeling of belonging for guests .
“It adds to their comfort , ” he said .
Some programs emphasize fitness .
<START:organization> Westin Hotels <END> introduced a Westin-New Balance equipment-lending program at more than 200 hotels in November 2012 .
The company estimates 30,000 guests a year participate .
<START:person> Peter Shankman <END> , an entrepreneur and author of the coming book “Zombie Loyalists ” was one .
Fourteen months ago , at a <START:organization> Westin <END> in <START:location> Atlanta <END> , he was up at 5 a.m. for a run before an early meeting .
After donning his shorts , he realized he forgot to pack running socks .
Expecting to run a 10-kilometer race three days later , he thought wearing dress socks for a seven-mile run that morning invited blisters .
The front desk staff offered him a free pair of running socks .
“They allowed me to continue on a schedule I preferred , which meant more to me than anything , ” he said .
Still , he has not traveled without his own equipment since .
A <START:organization> Westin <END> hotel typically charges $ 5 per stay for the socks , freshly laundered workout wear in a variety of sizes for both sexes , and sneakers that are cleaned and disinfected after each use .
The inner soles are changed monthly .
Fitness appeal takes different forms .
In July 2013 , <START:organization> Kimpton <END> , in partnership with Public , a <START:location> San Francisco <END> boutique bicycle and equipment company , introduced a fleet of Kimpton-branded bicycles that are free for guests to use .
Two to 10 bikes are available at 61 locations .
For guests who prefer four wheels , in March Loews introduced a chauffeur-driven car at five locations nationwide to take guests to nearby destinations .
Guests are responsible for their return transportation to the hotel .
At locations in <START:location> Miami <END> , <START:location> Hollywood <END> and <START:location> Santa Monica <END> , the hotels also offer free <START:organization> Fiat <END> loaner cars .
Even as loan programs can create greater loyalty and perhaps a willingness to pay a premium for a specific hotel , they have potential drawbacks , according to one expert , who sees the possibility that fewer guests will request items in the future , because of concerns about health and well-being .
“Some hotels may temporarily suspend these items as a precautionary response to protecting guest health and reducing liability , ” <START:person> Henry Harteveldt <END> , an analyst at <START:organization> Atmosphere Research Group <END> , wrote in an email .
For some guests , like <START:person> Ms. Barlow <END> , a preferred amenity is the ability to leave belongings behind .
<START:person> Mike DeFrino <END> , the chief operating officer at <START:organization> Kimpton Hotels <END> , said he had noticed at locations in <START:location> Cambridge , Mass. <END> , and <START:location> Cupertino , Calif. <END> , as many as 5 percent of guests are leaving bags behind .
“At <START:location> Cupertino <END> , they leave suits , ” he said .
“They don’t want to travel with blazers . ”
By accepting guest property for safekeeping , hotels run the risk of losing reputation and loyalty if something happens to it .
“The worst thing is to lose or misplace a guest item , ” <START:person> Mr. Hanson <END> said .
<START:person> Ms. Barlow <END> said she drew the line at leaving a laptop .
Still , even as her travel has abated , she said she missed staying long enough to establish a rapport with the hotel staff .
