http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/08/business/north-korea-denies-hacking-sony-but-calls-attack-a-righteous-deed.html
<START:location> SEOUL , South Korea <END> — <START:location> North Korea <END> on Sunday denied responsibility for hacking the computers of <START:organization> Sony Pictures <END> Entertainment but appeared to relish the attack that crippled the computer systems of the <START:location> Hollywood <END> company , which is set to release a comedy that involves a plot to assassinate its leader , <START:person> Kim Jong-un <END> .
<START:organization> Sony Pictures <END> is producing “a film abetting a terrorist act while hurting the dignity of the supreme leadership , ” a spokesman of the <START:organization> National Defense Commission <END> , <START:person> Mr. Kim’s <END> top governing agency in <START:location> Pyongyang <END> , was quoted as saying by the North’s <START:organization> Korean Central News Agency <END> .
The spokesman said <START:location> North Korea <END> did not know why <START:organization> Sony <END> was targeted , but he speculated that the attack “might be a righteous deed of the supporters and sympathizers with ” <START:location> North Korea <END> in its struggle to “put an end to U.S. imperialism . ”
A hacking attack last month shut down the computer systems of <START:organization> Sony Pictures <END> and exposed a trove of internal data , including salary figures .
<START:location> North Korea <END> has since emerged as a possible suspect because it has been criticizing <START:organization> Sony Pictures <END> for producing “The Interview , ” a comedy starring <START:person> Seth Rogen <END> and <START:person> James Franco <END> that involves the assassination plot against <START:person> Mr. Kim <END> .
<START:location> North Korea <END> saw no humor there .
It has called the movie “an act of war ” sponsored by <START:location> Washington <END> ’s “hostile policy . ”
<START:person> Mr. Kim’s <END> family has been ruling <START:location> North Korea <END> since the late 1940s with a totalitarian grip that has rested upon a personality cult .
The government in <START:location> Pyongyang <END> lashes out at any attempt from the outside to criticize <START:person> Mr. Kim <END> , calling it a challenge to the “supreme dignity ” of the entire country .
It has been especially sensitive about such criticism in recent weeks because there was an American-supported attempt at the <START:organization> United Nations <END> to ask the <START:organization> Security Council <END> to refer <START:person> Mr. Kim <END> to an international criminal court for human rights abuses .
No direct evidence has emerged yet that links <START:location> North Korea <END> to the hacking attack at <START:organization> Sony Pictures <END> , and digital-security analysts have been divided over the likelihood of its involvement .
On Sunday , <START:location> North Korea <END> said there were “a great number of supporters and sympathizers ” with <START:location> North Korea <END> “all over the world , ” including “champions of peace ” who might initiate more “righteous reaction ” against the <START:location> United States’ <END> “evildoings . ”
<START:location> South Korea <END>n and American officials have been increasingly concerned about <START:location> North Korea’s <END> capability to carry out attacks on computers , especially after huge disruptions of bank , government , media and military websites in <START:location> South Korea <END> in recent years that <START:location> South Korea <END> attributed to attacks sponsored by the North .
<START:location> North Korea <END> has denied involvement and instead blamed <START:location> South Korea <END> for disrupting its websites in recent years .
<START:location> North Korea <END> itself is cut off from the Internet , except for a handful of state-approved websites linked to the World Wide Web.
But <START:location> South Korea <END>n officials and defectors from <START:location> North Korea <END> said <START:location> North Korea <END> has been training specialists in computer attacks for decades to collect technological data through the Internet , spread the country ’s propaganda online and initiate hacking attacks .
In a report to <START:organization> Congress <END> last year , the <START:organization> United States Defense Department <END> said that given its bleak economic outlook , <START:location> North Korea <END> might see hacking attacks as “a cost-effective way to develop asymmetric , deniable military options . ”
In October , <START:location> South Korea’s <END> <START:organization> National Intelligence Service <END> told lawmakers that <START:location> North Korea <END>n-sponsored hackers had spread game apps containing malicious viruses from May through September , affecting an estimated 20,000 <START:location> South Korea <END>n smartphone users .
It did not reveal how it determined that such attacks were sponsored by <START:location> North Korea <END> .
