http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/08/business/obamas-net-neutrality-bid-divides-civil-rights-groups.html
<START:location> WASHINGTON <END> — When <START:person> President Obama <END> laid out his vision for strict regulation of Internet access last month , he was voicing views thought to be held by many at the most liberal end of the <START:organization> Democratic Party <END> .
A few days later , however , the <START:organization> N.A.A.C.P. <END> , the <START:organization> National Urban League <END> and the <START:organization> Rainbow/PUSH Coalition <END> sent representatives , including the <START:person> Rev. Jesse L. Jackson <END> , to tell <START:person> Tom Wheeler <END> , chairman of the <START:organization> Federal Communications Commission <END> , that they thought <START:person> Mr. Obama’s <END> call to regulate broadband Internet service as a utility would harm minority communities by stifling investment in underserved areas and entrenching already dominant Internet companies .
Their displeasure should not be read as a sign that most civil rights organizations were unhappy with <START:person> Mr. Obama’s <END> plan , however .
When it comes to the details of Internet regulation , groups that otherwise have much common ground simply don’t see eye to eye .
<START:organization> ColorofChange .org <END> , a black political coalition , and the <START:organization> National Hispanic Media Coalition <END> , for example , support treating Internet access as an essential service like electricity or water — as <START:person> Mr. Obama <END> proposed — while the <START:organization> League of United Latin American Citizens <END> opposes it .
“The civil rights community is like every sector anywhere .
While from the outside it seems like a monolith , it is not , ” said <START:person> Cheryl A. Leanza <END> , a policy adviser for the <START:organization> United Church of Christ <END> <START:organization> Office of Communication <END> .
Though she was part of the 11-member group that included <START:person> Mr. Jackson <END> , she asked the chairman to embrace the president ’s plan .
The debate is but one slice of a huge campaign to lobby the five <START:organization> F.C.C. <END> commissioners as they weigh net neutrality , the concept that all Internet traffic should be treated equally , and whether to reclassify broadband as a more heavily regulated service .
Since 2002 , broadband has been classified as a Title I information service under the Telecommunications Act of 1996 , meaning that the <START:organization> F.C.C. <END> lightly regulates it .
Title II services include “common carriers ” like telephone companies , whose rates the <START:organization> F.C.C. <END> can regulate and whose business plans often require the commission’s approval .
In May , <START:person> Mr. Wheeler <END> made a proposal that would allow companies to pay Internet providers to give them a “fast lane ” to consumers .
<START:person> Mr. Wheeler <END> is against that practice , known as paid prioritization , and he said his proposal would discourage it .
But the regulatory outline released by the <START:organization> F.C.C. <END> would still allow for paid prioritization in some circumstances , a loophole that was seized on by opponents .
<START:person> President Obama <END> urged the <START:organization> F.C.C. <END> to reclassify broadband as a Title II service , which would generally give the commission the authority to prohibit broadband providers from blocking or discriminating against legal online content .
In the four weeks since <START:person> Mr. Obama’s <END> move , over 100 companies , industry groups and coalitions have met with commissioners and their staffs .
At least 67 of those groups have met with <START:person> Mr. Wheeler <END> himself — nearly four a day , on average .
Included in those meetings have been civil rights groups with surprisingly divergent views .
The unusual alignments can also be seen in urban governments .
The cities of <START:location> Baltimore <END> , <START:location> Chicago <END> , <START:location> Los Angeles <END> and <START:location> San Francisco <END> sent representatives to meet with <START:person> Mr. Wheeler’s <END> advisers to say they agreed with tight regulation , but that view is opposed by the <START:organization> National Organization of Blacks in Government <END> .
“ I think we’re all on board with the values embedded in what <START:person> President Obama <END> said , things like accelerating broadband deployment and adoption , ” said <START:person> Nicol Turner-Lee <END> , vice president of the <START:organization> Minority Media and Telecommunications Council <END> and a member of the group including <START:person> Mr. Jackson <END> that met with the <START:organization> F.C.C. <END> chairman .
“The question is , will we be able to solve these issues by going so far with stringent regulation ? ”
Some of the groups that oppose Title II designation , like the <START:organization> Urban League <END> and the <START:organization> League of United Latin American Citizens <END> , have received contributions from organizations affiliated with Internet service providers , like the <START:organization> Comcast <END> Foundation , the charitable organization endowed by <START:organization> Comcast <END> .
Parts of the <START:organization> Rainbow/PUSH Coalition’s <END> annual symposium on civil rights were conducted last week at <START:organization> Comcast’s <END> offices in <START:location> Washington <END> .
But those organizations say that the donations or sponsorships do not influence their positions .
“We get support from people on all sides of the issue , including <START:organization> Google <END> and <START:organization> Facebook <END> , ” said <START:person> Brent A. Wilkes <END> , national executive director of the <START:organization> League of United Latin American Citizens <END> .
“We don’t let any of them influence our position . ”
Several of those favoring Title II , meanwhile , have received funding from organizations affiliated with companies that support stronger regulation .
The <START:organization> National Hispanic Media Coalition <END> conducts events that are sponsored in part by companies like <START:organization> Google <END> and <START:organization> Facebook <END> .
A trade organization sponsored by those and other Internet companies , the Internet Association , supports a shift to stricter regulation .
<START:person> Jessica Gonzalez <END> , executive vice president of the <START:organization> National Hispanic Media Coalition <END> , said her organization also received support from <START:organization> Comcast <END> for some of its programs .
“There is a clear separation between our policy work and who funds us , ” she said .
One of the primary disagreements among the civil rights groups is over a practice known as “zero rating , ” in which an Internet service provider makes a deal with a content provider like <START:organization> Facebook <END> or <START:organization> Spotify <END> to allow consumers unlimited access to that service without its counting against a cap on data usage .
Because zero-rating plans are most common among mobile broadband providers , those plans could particularly affect minority communities , <START:person> Ms. Turner-Lee <END> said , which are more likely to depend on mobile systems for Internet access .
It is not entirely clear how <START:person> Mr. Obama’s <END> plan would affect zero-rated apps .
“The relevant question is whether there is something to be said about zero-rating plans and the ways that they can be used to further Internet adoption , ” <START:person> Ms. Turner-Lee <END> said , adding that her group had not yet taken a stance .
But critics say that zero-rating programs are just a form of paid prioritization that could further entrench companies like <START:organization> Facebook <END> that have the financial muscle to pay for the privilege .
According to the Mobile Trends Charging Report by <START:organization> Allot Communications <END> , nearly half of mobile broadband providers worldwide offer at least one zero-rated app , and two-thirds of those offer <START:organization> Facebook <END> as one .
The alignment of civil rights groups both for and against <START:person> Mr. Obama’s <END> recommendation for net-neutrality enforcement is not the only oddity in this debate .
In 2005 , the <START:organization> Supreme Court <END> ruled that the F.C.C. acted within the law when it classified cable broadband as a lightly regulated information service .
Writing a stinging dissent to that decision — that is , saying that broadband was obviously more like a utility — was an otherwise frequent nemesis of Democrats : <START:person> Justice Antonin Scalia <END> .
