http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/27/world/asia/pakistan-militants-drone.html
<START:location> PESHAWAR , Pakistan <END> — At least nine people suspected of being militants , including four foreigners , were killed in two separate drone strikes in northwestern <START:location> Pakistan <END> on Friday , a Pakistani security official said .
The strikes , which the official said were believed to have been carried out by American drones , took place in the remote <START:location> Shawal Valley <END> of the <START:location> North Waziristan <END> tribal region , which has long been a redoubt for militants from the <START:organization> Taliban <END> and <START:organization> Al Qaeda <END> .
The security official said the first strike targeted a vehicle about 40 miles west of <START:location> North Waziristan’s <END> regional headquarters , <START:person> Miram Shah <END> .
“ What we have heard is that four Uzbeks were killed in that strike , ” the official said , speaking on the condition of anonymity because he was not authorized to talk to the news media .
In the second strike , a drone fired two missiles into a compound in <START:location> Kund Sar <END> in the <START:location> Shawal Valley <END> , targeting the base of the <START:organization> Punjabi Taliban <END> leader , <START:person> Asmatullah Muawiyah <END> , and killing five people , the official said .
The identities of those killed remained unknown , and it was not clear if <START:person> Mr. Muawiyah <END> was at the base when the strike occurred .
He announced in September that his group would focus on <START:location> Afghanistan <END> and not carry out attacks inside <START:location> Pakistan <END> , in a sign of the differences between <START:organization> Taliban <END> militants .
The strikes on Friday came as the Pakistani military continues an offensive against <START:organization> Taliban <END> and foreign militants in <START:location> North Waziristan <END> .
The offensive , Operation Zarb-e-Azb , began in June .
The military says that it has taken control of 90 percent of the region and that it has killed at least 2,100 militants .
However , no independent verification of the reported casualties was possible because the region is closed to members of the foreign news media .
Pakistani security officials say that most of the local and foreign militants who have escaped the military operation in the <START:location> Miram Shah <END> and <START:location> Mir Ali <END> areas of <START:location> North Waziristan <END> have taken sanctuary in the densely forested <START:location> Shawal Valley <END> .
The attack this month on a school in <START:location> Peshawar <END> that killed 149 people , including 132 children , has caused <START:location> Pakistan’s <END> civilian and military leadership to step up operations against militants .
<START:person> Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif <END> has also announced the formation of military courts for the speedy prosecution in terrorism cases , which the military has long demanded .
