http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/08/business/ralph-h-baer-dies-inventor-of-odyssey-first-system-for-home-video-games.html
<START:person> Ralph H. Baer <END> , who turned television sets into electronic fantasy lands by inventing and patenting the first home video game system , died on Saturday at his home in <START:location> Manchester , N.H. <END>
He was 92 .
His death was confirmed by his family .
Video games have become more than just a ubiquitous pastime and a gigantic market ( by some estimates , total worldwide sales of console hardware and software and online , mobile and computer games exceeded $ 90 billion in 2013 ) .
They are also an engine that has driven scientists and engineers to multiply computer speed , memory and visualization to today’s staggering capabilities .
Flash back to the sultry late summer of 1966 : <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> is sitting on a step outside the <START:organization> Port Authority <END> Bus Terminal in <START:location> Manhattan <END> waiting for a colleague .
By profession , he is an engineer overseeing 500 employees at a military contractor .
Today , a vision has gripped him , and he begins scribbling furiously on a yellow legal pad with a No. 2 pencil .
The result was a detailed four-page outline for a “game box ” that would allow people to play board , action , sports and other games on almost any American television set .
An intrigued boss gave him $ 2,000 for research and $ 500 for materials and assigned two men to work with him .
For all three , as they plowed through prototype after prototype in a secret workshop , the project became an obsession .
In March 1971 , <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> and his employer , <START:organization> Sanders Associates <END> in <START:location> Nashua , N.H. <END> , filed for the first video game patent , which was granted in April 1973 as Patent No. 3,728,480 .
It made an extraordinarily large claim to a legal monopoly for any product that included a domestic television with circuits capable of producing and controlling dots on a screen .
<START:organization> Sanders Associates <END> licensed its system to <START:organization> Magnavox <END> , which began selling it as <START:organization> Odyssey <END> in the summer of 1972 as the first home video game console .
It sold 130,000 units the first year .
<START:organization> Odyssey <END> consisted of a master control unit containing all the electronic gear , two player control units that directed players on the TV screen , and a set of electronic program cards , each of which supported a different game .
Plastic overlays that clung to the screen to supply color were included .
To supplement the electronic action , a deck of playing cards , poker chips and a pair of dice were included .
But the guts of the device were what mattered : 40 transistors and 40 diodes .
That hardware ran everything .
<START:organization> Odyssey <END> , often called the first home computing device , had no software .
Several months after <START:organization> Odyssey <END> hit the market , <START:organization> Atari <END> came out with the first arcade video game , <START:organization> Pong <END> .
Though <START:organization> Pong <END> became better known than <START:organization> Odyssey <END> and was in some ways more agile , <START:organization> Sanders <END> and <START:organization> Magnavox <END> immediately saw it as an infringement on their patent .
They sued <START:organization> Atari <END> in 1974 for usurping their rights .
<START:organization> Atari <END> settled with them by paying $ 700,000 to become <START:organization> Odyssey’s <END> second licensee .
Over the next 20 years , <START:organization> Magnavox <END> went on to sue dozens more companies , winning more than $ 100 million .
<START:person> Mr. Baer <END> often testified .
<START:organization> “Magnavox <END> is n’t in the business of making video games , ” <START:person> Howard Lincoln <END> , <START:organization> Nintendo’s <END> vice president and senior counsel , groused in an interview with <START:organization> Newsday <END> in 1989 .
“They’re just in the business of suing people . ”
( <START:organization> Nintendo <END> , like all the game makers <START:organization> Magnavox <END> challenged , lost . )
<START:person> Mr. Baer’s <END> contraption represented the beginnings of a change in man’s relationship with machines .
<START:person> Harold Goldberg <END> , in his book “All Your Base Are Belong to Us : How Fifty Years of Videogames Conquered Pop Culture ” ( 2011 ) , said <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> made television “an extension of you , the player . ”
“It would let you interact with a square on a black-and-white screen , and if you had even the lamest imagination , it made you believe you were volleying at tennis , aiming carefully as a brave marksman , even playing the innocent as you saved lives , ” <START:person> Mr. Goldberg <END> wrote .
The roots of video games go back to universities and research laboratories .
Some experts cite <START:person> William A. Higinbotham’s <END> <START:organization> Tennis for Two <END> , invented in 1958 at <START:organization> Brookhaven National Laboratory <END> , as the first interactive computer game .
“ When technology is ready for something novel , when the components needed to build something new become affordable , it is going to be done by someone and more likely by several people , ” wrote <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> , who said he had never seen <START:organization> Tennis for Two <END> .
From <START:person> Mr. Baer’s <END> modestly named “brown box ” have sprung <START:organization> PlayStation <END> , <START:organization> Xbox <END> and <START:organization> Wii <END> , all products of the ceaseless revolution in microprocessing .
Two technical paths merged to power this revolution .
One was computer science ; the other was <START:person> Mr. Baer’s <END> field of expertise , television engineering .
<START:person> Mr. Baer <END> had more than 150 <START:location> United States <END> and foreign patents , and his contributions ranged from talking doormats and greeting cards to submarine tracking systems .
In 2006 , <START:person> President George W. Bush <END> awarded him the National Medal of Technology .
In 2010 , he was admitted to the <START:organization> National Inventors Hall of Fame <END> .
Along with <START:person> Howard Morrison <END> , he invented the electronic game <START:organization> Simon <END> , which was introduced at <START:organization> Studio 54 <END> in <START:location> Manhattan <END> in 1978 and became a pop culture phenomenon in the 1980s .
A saucer-shaped plastic toy with four colored buttons , it lit up and emitted tones in a sequence that the player then had to reproduce .
It is still being sold .
“Coming up with novel ideas and converting them into real products has always been as natural as breathing for me , ” <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> wrote in his 2005 autobiography , “Videogames : In the Beginning . ”
<START:person> Ralph Henry Baer <END> was born on March 8 , 1922 , into a Jewish family in <START:location> Pirmasens , Germany <END> , where his father worked in a shoe factory .
His family emigrated to <START:location> New York <END> in 1938 to escape <START:person> Hitler <END> and settled in the <START:location> Bronx <END> .
Within a week , <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> , then 16 , was working from 8 a.m. to 6 p.m. in a factory that made leather cases for manicure kits .
He soon invented a machine to speed the process by stitching five or six at once .
One day on the subway he noticed an advertisement in a magazine somebody else was reading .
“Make big money in radio and television servicing , ” it said .
So <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> spent a quarter of his $ 12 in wages every week on a correspondence course .
He finished in a few months , then took the advanced course .
He quit the factory after two years and fixed radios .
He was drafted into the <START:organization> Army <END> in 1943 and became an intelligence officer .
He served in <START:location> Europe <END> during World War II , and in his spare time studied algebra and made radios from German mine detectors so his friends could listen to music .
Trained to be an expert in small arms , he collected 18 tons of German weapons , which were exhibited at military museums in the <START:location> United States <END> .
After the war , <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> attended the <START:organization> American Television Institute of Technology <END> in <START:location> Chicago <END> , where he earned one of the first bachelor’s degrees in television engineering .
He then worked for a company that made surgical cutting machines , before joining <START:organization> Loral Electronics <END> in the <START:location> Bronx <END> as a senior engineer .
Assigned to design a state-of-the art television set in 1951 , he suggested adding a game-playing feature .
“Forget it , ” he recalled his boss saying .
“ Just build the damn TV set ; you’re behind schedule as it is . ”
In 1956 <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> joined <START:organization> Sanders <END> , where he advanced to division manager .
As he pursued military projects like electronic devices to teach weapons aiming , his mind returned to the idea of a TV set with a game feature .
Those musings led to his eureka moment at the <START:location> New York <END> bus station .
Still , he said in 2007 , the common reaction of most <START:organization> Sanders <END> executives was , “Are you still screwing around with that stuff ? ”
One top boss , however , saw potential in <START:person> Mr. Baer’s <END> idea .
He assigned two engineers , <START:person> Bill Harrison <END> and <START:person> Bill Rusch <END> , to work with him , and gave the three $ 2,500 to spend .
In a tiny room <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> described as an attic , they worked in secret , building seven prototypes .
<START:organization> Sanders <END> first tried to license it to pay-TV companies , the forerunners of today’s cable systems , but found no takers .
Television manufacturers were also lukewarm .
<START:organization> RCA <END> expressed interest but backed out .
<START:organization> Magnavox <END> then signed on .
The <START:organization> Odyssey <END> had sold some 330,000 units by 1975 , but <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> thought it could have sold many more .
He blamed <START:organization> Magnavox <END> for limiting sales to its own dealers , giving the false impression that the system worked only on <START:organization> Magnavox <END> sets .
He also criticized the company for pricing it at $ 100 , rather than the $ 19.95 he recommended .
<START:organization> Odyssey <END> nonetheless represented a critical point .
Along with <START:organization> Atari’s <END> <START:organization> Pong, <END> which had more advanced electronics and sound , it moved games into a faster , more complex realm , to the delight of an eager new audience .
The accomplishment , <START:person> Mr. Baer <END> wrote , would amount to far more than just fun and games .
“If it weren’t for video game enthusiasts and the absolute commercial need to keep them happy with ever-better graphics requiring ever-higher processor speeds , complex computer graphics would still be found only in the high-priced domains of the business and science world , ” he said .
In an interview , <START:person> Keith Feinstein <END> , a video game historian , called <START:person> Mr. Baer’s <END> invention “the beginning of a revolution in thought . ”
<START:person> Mr. Baer <END> retired from <START:organization> Sanders <END> in 1987 and started his own consulting business .
<START:person> Mr. Baer <END> is survived by two sons , <START:person> James <END> and <START:person> Mark <END> ; a daughter , <START:person> Nancy Baer <END> ; and four grandchildren .
His wife of 53 years , the former <START:person> Dena Whinston <END> , died in 2006 .
<START:person> Mr. Baer <END> donated his collection of early game hardware to several museums , including the <START:organization> Smithsonian Institution <END> .
