He keeps grade cards for every member of Congress , deploys three million activists to blast lawmakers with anti-immigration telephone calls , faxes and emails , and runs a website where his followers have called undocumented immigrants “criminal invaders ” and “wolves at the door . ”
But for <START:person> Roy H. Beck <END> , perhaps the most powerful member of the small but vocal movement that has helped scuttle every effort at an immigration overhaul for nearly two decades , the fight is only beginning .
Over the next year , his goal is to cut off funding for President Obama’s executive actions that have shielded up to five million people from deportation and will allow many of them work permits .
“There’s a good chance that we’ll roll back a good share of this , ” <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> , 66 , said in a recent interview in his <START:location> Rosslyn , Va. <END> , office , a mostly threadbare space with sweeping views of the <START:location> Potomac River <END> and the <START:location> Capitol <END> dome .
“We did as much as possible to make immigration radioactive in as many places as possible . ”
As the founder and president of <START:organization> NumbersUSA <END> , <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> has 35 staff members and an annual budget of about $ 10 million compared with a coalition of immigrant groups that spent $ 1.5 billion from 2008 to 2012 lobbying for an array of immigration changes , according to an estimate by the nonpartisan <START:organization> Sunlight Foundation <END> .
But what <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> lacks in resources , he makes up for in impact .
<START:person> Mr. Beck <END> and his group “have succeeded in thwarting the passage of comprehensive immigration reform by generating popular anger on the right that overwhelmed mainstream Republicans , ” said <START:person> Frank Sharry <END> of <START:organization> America’s Voice <END> , an advocacy group pressing for such an overhaul .
At the very least , immigration advocates say , they will have to fight the grass-roots uproar that <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> has fueled .
<START:person> Mr. Beck <END> , a former environmental journalist who once worked at <START:organization> The Grand Rapids Press <END> and <START:organization> The Cincinnati Enquirer <END> , said he did not feel the rage toward immigrants that he is able to marshal in others .
He said that he voted for <START:person> Mr. Obama <END> in 2008 , and he is consistently described by his critics as genial and nonconfrontational .
But he says that the rise in immigration levels is destroying the <START:location> United States <END> — both the environment and employment opportunities for the working class — and is angry at what he considers complicity by the government on the immigrants ’ behalf .
While the country once admitted about 250,000 legal immigrants annually , he said , the number has ballooned to one million , which does not include those who come illegally .
<START:person> Mr. Beck <END> is pressing to cut legal immigration to 500,000 people a year .
“This has nothing to do with the immigrants themselves , ” <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> said .
“ But are the people who are here illegally more important than the Americans , the people of this national community , who have absolutely been robbed of their dignity ? ”
Despite his disclaimers , <START:person> Mr. Beck’s <END> critics say he is pushing a xenophobic agenda and is the benign face of a racist movement .
“ He’s played footsie with extremists all along , ” said <START:person> Heidi Beirich <END> , the director of the <START:organization> Southern Poverty Law Center <END> ’s <START:organization> Intelligence Project <END> , which tracks hate groups .
Even as she described <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> as a “completely nice guy , ” <START:person> Ms. Beirich <END> said that “in a way , what Beck does is , he provides cover for the bad guys . ”
The criticism stems from <START:person> Mr. Beck’s <END> connection to <START:person> John H. Tanton <END> , a <START:location> Michigan <END> ophthalmologist who helped start and finance <START:organization> NumbersUSA <END> and has nurtured two other groups , the <START:organization> Federation for American Immigration Reform <END> and the <START:organization> Center for Immigration Studies <END> , which share <START:person> Mr. Beck’s <END> commitment to reducing immigration .
<START:person> Mr. Beck <END> described him as “one of the grand environmental leaders , ” but <START:person> Mr. Tanton <END> has also been accused of pushing a white nationalist agenda , and he once wrote of his fear of a “Latino onslaught . ”
<START:person> Mr. Beck <END> said that his group had been independent of <START:person> Mr. Tanton <END> for a dozen years , and he went out of his way to deny charges of racism .
He has a “No to Immigrant Bashing ” section on the <START:organization> NumbersUSA <END> website urging civil discourse , and said he filtered out user comments that contain overtly racist terms .
He has also posted a photograph of <START:person> Barbara Jordan <END> , a <START:location> Texas <END> congresswoman and civil rights leader who was the chairwoman of an immigration commission he advised in 1996 , doing so in part , <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> said , to ward off racist members .
“If you’re a white supremacy group , that ’s sort of a signal to you that , ‘This is not our group , ’ ” <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> said .
Tax disclosures filed in 2013 show that <START:organization> NumbersUSA <END> received about $ 4.5 million from the <START:organization> Colcom Foundation <END> , a Pittsburgh-based organization founded by <START:person> Cordelia Scaife May <END> , the <START:organization> Mellon <END> banking heiress .
The foundation says it works to combat overpopulation ; the <START:organization> Southern Poverty Law Center <END> says the foundation funds hate groups with “nativist ” missions .
The foundation’s vice president of philanthropy is <START:person> John F. Rohe <END> , a <START:organization> Tanton <END> loyalist and biographer .
<START:organization> Numbers USA <END> , <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> said , has “always stayed away from cultural issues . ”
From his earliest days , <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> focused on numbers .
Now the father of two adult sons , he was raised in <START:location> Marshfield <END> , a town of 2,500 in <START:location> Missouri’s Ozarks <END> , where he delivered milk and collected cans to make pocket money .
After journalism school at the <START:organization> University of Missouri <END> , <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> became interested in immigration while covering the birth of the environmental movement in the late 1960s , as concern grew about the consequences of population growth on natural resources .
Disillusioned when he thought immigration was not receiving sufficient attention , he left journalism in the 1990s to write books , and later decided to start <START:organization> Numbers USA <END> .
He began with a video , recorded on VHS tape in 1996 , in which he used a huge container of colored gumballs to illustrate the billions of people living in third world countries , and a small glass snifter to portray the <START:location> United States <END> , taking in millions more immigrants , one gumball at a time .
The gumballs are still in his office , but on a recent afternoon , he left them behind and instead took PowerPoint slides to make his arguments to a group of students from <START:organization> Grinnell College <END> in <START:location> Iowa <END> who are spending a semester in <START:location> Washington <END> .
“At the end , unless somebody’s watching the numbers , you end up with a problem , ” <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> told the group .
“It sounds horrible , does n’t it ? ”
<START:person> Mr. Beck <END> conceded of his group ’s position that immigration should be sharply curtailed and strict new workplace screenings instituted , so any undocumented worker is immediately laid off .
“People say , ‘Boy that ’s really mean — it ’s so mean — because you’re making that person who has a job lose a job , ’ ” <START:person> Mr. Beck <END> told his young audience .
“And yet , as long as they’re in that job , what’s the meanest thing of all ?
The Americans that don’t have that job . ”
