http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/12/05/uber-to-portland-were-here-deal-with-it/
Rules , schmules .
As many people in <START:location> Portland , Ore. <END> , left work to return home on Friday evening , <START:organization> Uber <END> , the ride-hailing start-up , began offering rides in that city for the first time , despite loud protests from local officials who have deemed the service illegal .
That devil-may-care approach to dealing with city officials — entering a city without permission and dealing with regulatory issues after its services are well established and locals are already hooked — has become a hallmark of <START:organization> Uber’s <END> strategy .
In October , <START:organization> Uber <END> began its service in <START:location> Las Vegas <END> , where it was deemed illegal ; multiple drivers were cited within hours of the company ’s debut there .
Similar scenarios played out in <START:location> Austin , Tex . <END> , <START:location> Philadelphia <END> and other cities around the country .
But <START:organization> Uber’s <END> move in <START:location> Portland <END> comes just days after it vowed in a blog post to become a “ smarter and more humble company . ”
<START:organization> Uber <END> , which is now valued at more than $ 40 billion , is reeling from a string of recent embarrassments that have critics questioning its ethics .
The company ’s executives have been accused of taking a lax approach to customer privacy , among other criticisms .
In <START:location> Portland <END> , the commissioner in charge of the city ’s <START:organization> Bureau of Transportation <END> was furious enough at <START:organization> Uber <END> that he suggested <START:location> Portland <END> should amend its regulations to allow <START:organization> Lyft <END> — one of <START:organization> Uber’s <END> biggest competitors — instead of <START:organization> Uber <END> , to operate in the city .
On his <START:organization> Facebook <END> page , the mayor threatened fines for the company and its drivers .
“People should know that <START:organization> Uber’s <END> action is illegal , ” <START:person> Mayor Charlie Hales <END> said in the post .
“The city will enforce existing regulations .
That could include fines for the company , as well as fines for drivers . ”
<START:organization> Uber’s <END> service , which allows users to summon a private car with a smartphone app , has become hugely popular in the five years since it was started .
The service has ballooned and now operates in more than 250 cities in 50 countries .
<START:organization> Uber’s <END> arrival in <START:location> Portland <END> has been something of an inevitability .
The service has been available in more than a dozen cities surrounding the greater <START:location> Portland <END> area for months , and the company has been in talks with <START:location> Portland <END> .
“We’ve been talking to them for over a year , and we will continue to talk with them , ” said Eva Behrend , an <START:organization> Uber <END> spokeswoman .
But <START:location> Portland <END> transportation officials have fought to examine current regulatory statutes before allowing the service to operate in the city .
<START:person> Steve Novick <END> , the commissioner of the Bureau of Transportation , said he learned of <START:organization> Uber’s <END> intentions to set up shop earlier today when he received a text message from a reporter that said , “<START:organization> Uber <END> tells me they’re launching at 5 , do you have anything to say ? ”
Not long after , <START:person> Mr. Novick <END> and <START:person> Mr. Hales <END> were on a conference call with <START:organization> Uber’s <END> senior vice president for policy and strategy , <START:person> David Plouffe <END> , the former political strategist who ran <START:person> President Obama’s <END> 2008 campaign .
<START:person> “Plouffe <END> said , ‘ Well , you know we’re active in these markets and we’re providing a service and there is great demand in <START:location> Oregon <END> and blah blah blah , ’ ” <START:person> Mr. Novick <END> said .
“ I said , ‘Mr.
<START:person> Plouffe <END> , announcing that you’re going to break the law is not civil . ’
”
<START:person> Mr. Novick <END> added : “This is not about whether we should have a thoughtful conversation about changing taxi regulations — we’re up for that .
This is about one company thinking it is above the law . ”
If and when <START:location> Portland <END> amends its regulations to allow ride-sharing services like <START:organization> Uber <END> , <START:person> Mr. Novick <END> said he wished there were some way for him to still prohibit <START:organization> Uber <END> from coming to <START:location> Portland <END> .
“ I don’t know if this is legally feasible , but my inclination would be to allow <START:organization> Lyft <END> here a long time before <START:organization> Uber <END> , ” he said .
<START:organization> “Lyft <END> seems like a respectable company , and <START:organization> Uber <END> seems like a bunch of thugs . ”
But <START:organization> Uber <END> does not show signs of slowing down .
“The statement by <START:person> Commissioner Novick <END> shows a real disregard for consumer demand , choice and what the people of <START:location> Portland <END> want , ” <START:person> Ms. Behrend <END> , the <START:organization> Uber <END> spokeswoman , said .
