http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2014/12/08/with-bank-of-america-order-s-e-c-breaks-the-mold/
The recidivism rate among companies caught violating securities laws can be a bit disheartening .
Despite settlements that include corporate proclamations of a commitment to compliance , the same names seem to appear again and again in settlements for new violations .
The <START:organization> Securities and Exchange Commission <END> has recently taken a small step toward making the cost of a violation a bit steeper by refusing to give companies a free pass .
In August , <START:organization> Bank of America <END> reached a $ 16.65 billion settlement with the <START:organization> Justice Department <END> over accusations that it duped investors into buying troubled residential mortgage-backed securities .
As part of that settlement , the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> resolved charges of securities fraud .
That case was fairly small , requiring the bank to pay about $ 135 million for selling a security that resulted in heavy losses to investors .
But getting the settlement approved was held up until late last month because the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END>’s commissioners could not agree on granting the bank a waiver from rules that could prevent it from selling certain investments .
That would have had a significant effect on its <START:organization> Merrill Lynch <END> subsidiary by cutting off access to certain types of hedge fund investments , a lucrative segment of the market that would probably cost it clients .
<START:organization> S.E.C. <END> Rule 506 permits sales of an unlimited amount of securities to “accredited investors , ” generally defined as those with the financial wherewithal to fend for themselves that do not need the protections provided by the disclosure requirements in the law .
This avenue is used annually to sell hundreds of billions of dollars in investments to large investors , like hedge funds and pension plans , and is a significant avenue for raising capital .
In the Dodd-Frank Act , <START:organization> Congress <END> directed the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> to write a “bad actor” rule .
That rule does n’t allow the exemption if the issuer of the securities or its underwriters was subject to a judicial or administrative order for engaging in fraud or similar types of violations , like failing to maintain adequate books and records .
Adopted in 2013 as an amendment to Rule 506 , it imposes a five-year ban on participating in securities offerings unless the firm can convince the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> that there is good cause “that it is not necessary under the circumstances . ”
There is another “bad actor” rule important to large companies like <START:organization> Bank of America <END> that routinely access the securities markets to raise capital .
Under Rule 405 , a “well-known seasoned issuer ” does not have to submit its offering documents in advance for review by the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> before selling securities , allowing it to act quickly when market conditions are favorable .
Like Rule 506 , this provision cannot be used by a company subject to an order prohibiting violations of the anti-fraud provisions of the securities laws as part of a settlement .
But it can be waived for “good cause . ”
Those waivers had become routine after a settlement with the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END>
Some companies , in fact , received multiple waivers .
But last April , <START:person> Kara M. Stein <END> , one of the five commissioners , dissented from the order granting a waiver to the <START:organization> Royal Bank of Scotland <END> after one of its subsidiaries pleaded guilty to manipulating the <START:location> London <END> interbank offered rate , or Libor .
In a statement , <START:person> Ms. Stein <END> warned that by routinely granting such waivers , the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> “may have enshrined a new policy — that some firms are just too big to bar . ”
That warning came to haunt <START:organization> Bank of America <END> when it sought a waiver from the bad actor exclusion under Rule 506 after its mortgage-backed security settlement .
The bank was a victim of circumstances because <START:person> Mary Jo White <END> , the chairwoman of the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> , had to recuse herself from the case because of her prior representation of <START:person> Kenneth D. Lewis <END> , the bank’s former chief executive .
<START:organization> Bloomberg <END> reported that the four remaining commissioners were split 2 to 2 on whether to grant a waiver , with <START:person> Ms. Stein’s <END> fellow Democratic commissioner , <START:person> Luis A. Aguilar <END> , joining her in holding up approval of the settlement until the waiver issue could be resolved .
The settlement was finally approved right before Thanksgiving when <START:organization> Bank of America <END> agreed to appoint an outside monitor “not unacceptable ” to the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> to conduct a comprehensive review of its compliance with Rule 506 in exchange for a waiver of the bad actor ban .
Importantly , the waiver is only good for 30 months , so <START:organization> Bank of America <END> will have to come back to the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> to show there is good cause for a waiver of the rest of the five-year prohibition .
The order also does not grant a waiver from the ban in Rule 405 on bad actors using the well-known seasoned issuer exemption .
Although it is likely that <START:organization> Bank of America <END> will seek such a waiver in the future , for the moment , it will be a bit more difficult for the bank to quickly access the securities markets .
With settlements looming for big banks over their role in manipulation of foreign exchange rates , the question is whether the treatment of <START:organization> Bank of America <END> will become the norm for obtaining waivers from the bad actor rules or whether the <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> will revert to its earlier pattern of routinely granting those requests .
The circumstances requiring <START:organization> Bank of America <END> to work hard for a waiver were unusual because <START:person> Ms. White’s <END> withdrawal from the case led to the even split between the remaining commissioners .
So it could be a one-time situation .
One issue that has divided the commission is whether to view the bad actor rules as another form of punishment for a violation , or as a remedy limited to violations that directly involve a company ’s financial reporting .
A Republican commissioner , <START:person> Daniel M. Gallagher <END> , issued a statement in April arguing that “the punishment-focused view ” of waivers of the well-known seasoned issuer rule “is even more troubling ” because the harm is inflicted on shareholders from the increased costs of issuing securities .
“We must have a robust waiver program to appropriately distinguish between cases when disqualification is and is not justified , ” he said .
In a speech on Dec. 4 , <START:person> Ms. Stein <END> celebrated the aggressive approach taken with <START:organization> Bank of America <END> , stating that “we should be flexible and nuanced in our approach to these waivers , so that we make the most of this powerful tool . ”
She described the <START:organization> Bank of America <END> order as “a breakthrough in the commission’s method of handling waivers , and I hope to see more of this and other thoughtful approaches in the future . ”
The terms of <START:organization> Bank of America <END>’s waiver that require appointment of a monitor are not particularly onerous .
But they are a change from the days when granting such requests was almost a matter of routine .
No agency wants to be known as going soft on the companies it regulates , and the bad actor rules had become like sending a child to the time-out chair at home — a mild threat that was easily discarded once the appropriate apology was made .
The <START:organization> S.E.C. <END> is likely to take a tougher stance in agreeing to waivers of the bad actor prohibition , which means defense lawyers will have to consider the waiver issue right from the start rather than assuming the agency will rubber-stamp requests .
