http://www.latimes.com/world/afghanistan-pakistan/la-fg-pakistan-taliban-attack-20141216-story.html
Pakistani <START:organization> Taliban <END> militants stormed an army-run school on Tuesday and killed at least 104 people , including 84 children , shooting some in the head , while hundreds of teachers and students were trapped inside the building , officials said .
Pakistani security forces mounted a rescue operation at the school in <START:location> Peshawar <END> , the capital of northeastern <START:location> Pakistan’s <END> <START:location> Khyber Pakhtunkhwa <END> province .
Chief executive <START:person> Pervez Khattak <END> said that 104 people were killed , including the 84 students , all of whom were believed to be younger than 14 .
Teachers and one member of the security forces were also reported killed .
More than 80 others were wounded , some critically , said hospital officials , who pleaded with the public for blood donations .
Eight to 10 gunmen wearing the uniforms of security forces entered the <START:organization> Army Public School and College <END> school around 11 a.m. and broke into an auditorium where ninth and tenth grade students were listening to a lecture , <START:person> Khattak <END> said .
About three hours later , four to five gunmen remained holed up in the office of the school principal , <START:person> Khattak <END> told reporters outside <START:organization> Lady Reading Hospital <END> , where many of the injured were being treated .
One attacker blew himself up whole two others were killed by security forces , he said .
A teacher said that he was conducting an exam at the college section when he heard a burst of gunfire .
A teenage student who was rescued by security forces said he saw a gunman of about 25 years old firing indiscriminately at students .
The student , who requested anonymity , said the number of dead and injured could be very high .
“One of my classmates was dead , ” he said .
“As the army personnel rescued us and ushered us out , I saw many injured too . ”
Some of the injured were taken to <START:organization> Combined Military Hospital <END> 10 minutes away , while others were brought to <START:organization> Lady Reading Hospital <END> .
“Many are in the operation theater are now in critical condition , undergoing treatment , ” said <START:person> Ejaz Khan <END> , a <START:organization> Lady Reading Hospital <END> official .
A spokesman for the Pakistani <START:organization> Taliban <END> claimed responsibility for the attack and said it was retaliation for the Pakistani military ’s months-long offensive in northeastern Pakistan’s tribal areas , which has killed an unknown number of militants .
The school , which teaches children from kindergarten through tenth grade , is attended mainly by children of army personnel .
A <START:organization> Taliban <END> spokesman , <START:person> Muhammad Khorsani <END> , told <START:location> Pakistan’s <END> <START:organization> Express Tribune <END> newspaper : “We will target every institution linked to the army unless they stop operations and the extrajudicial killing of our detainees , ” he said .
The Pakistani <START:organization> Taliban <END> has carried out brazen attacks on civilians and against students before , but this was by far the biggest and deadliest operation it has ever launched against children .
“The news from <START:location> Pakistan <END> is deeply shocking , ” tweeted <START:person> British Prime Minister David Cameron <END> .
“It 's horrifying that children are being killed simply for going to school . ”
<START:person> Ali <END> is a special correspondent .
Staff writer Bengali reported from <START:location> Mumbai , India <END> .
